Theo.com
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels.
demons and saints. In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular
materialism to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate
everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen
Damick and Father Stephen De Young host this live-colon show focused on Enchantment in creation.
the union of the scene.
and unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind
throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Thank you so much, Voice of Steve.
Good evening, Giants Killers.
And I said Giants Killers.
Oh boy, like the New York Giants.
Giants Killers, Dragon Slayers.
Your listening to Lord of Spirits podcast,
my co-host Father Stephen D'Young
is with me from Cajun Country, Lafayette, Louisiana.
My I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick in exiling
Yankee country in a May as Pennsylvania. If you're listening to us live you can call
and at 855 AF radio that's 8552372346. Monteshka Trudy as usual will be taking your calls this
evening which we're going to get to in the second part of our show. Before we get to that though,
on October 26 through 29, 2023. At the Antioch in Village in Western Pennsylvania we are going to
to be holding the first ever.
Lord of Spirits Conference. Father Stephen and I are going to both be there. We're
going to be giving talks and also will be there. Father's David Subu and
Lucas Christensen and we are also very happy to announce that his eminence
Archbishop Alexander Galitson will be speaking as well and there is going to
be an RPG tournament which is the only part that really matters to Father
Steven first
Dungeons and Dragons tournament.
Don't bury the lead. We're not playing mutants and mastermind.
We're not going to play merch.
It's the only part that really matters. Period. Period.
Yeah.
Well, the schedule is going to be still being worked on.
But you can find all the current details and you can register by going to store.
that enginefeath.com slash events.
It's gonna be fun.
I'm hoping at least one person would be wearing a bat costume.
Never know.
It seems possible.
Anyway, that being said,
tonight we're going to be talking about the Holy Mystery of Ordination,
the actual ritual act that makes a man part of ordained ministry.
This is now the fourth in our series on the sacraments of the Church,
but how many episodes will there be?
Five, seven, nine, twenty-three.
Who knows?
So far
this episode though is all about the priesthood, right?
No.
We did that one already.
We already did that one.
And like you just said, what it was about.
That's true.
But people say ordination priesthood.
So this is the latest, we need to, we're going to be meeting our listeners.
That's true.
They're going to actually see us in person.
Right.
And so I feel like we need to begin now to be more transparent.
Right, like about...
the strains in our interpersonal relationship.
Because I don't know if you're talking.
I don't know if you're the talk.
But they say we've got nothing in common.
No common ground to start from.
Wow.
And we're falling apart.
But as we were talking about it earlier today, I said,
hey, what about breakfast at Tiffany's?
And you said I think I remember the film is I recall we both kind of liked
And you know that's all that's the one thing we got yeah
Wow, that's got to be what it was at 1990
Five
I'm trying to remember when that song came out somewhere around there. Yeah, man
You got a reference too, so there's one hit wonder I did
This would be the one I get for the show. Yeah
That's gotta be a bingo square, right?
father Andrew gets a reference. Right. I feel like people should get a Lord of
Spinegoes Square for that. Yeah. So yes, this episode is not about the priesthood as such.
Right. Because we already did that. Then they're done that.
Available for download at your local ancient faith.com. For free by the way.
All you guys who complain like this is free. No one's making you pay to listen to this.
So just saying, are there people out there complaining they have to pay for podcasts?
I don't think they have to pay.
They're just complaining about the podcasts, you know?
Oh, well, you get what you pay for.
Right.
So you get three hours of free something.
So you can go and listen to that one.
you want to refresh her there will be some things tonight that connect to
with that. And so that might be a worthwhile thing to do. If you're caught up, if you want
to excuse to have headphones in during a family gathering over the holidays this weekend.
And then when they ask what you're listening to, you can sound spiritual instead of antisocial,
right? So life hack. So we're not talking about presid. We're also not, when we say that
this episode we're talking about ordination.
We're not.
talking about contemporary American practice or elsewhere of how that works, how seminaries
work, and how pastoral education is done.
That sort of thing mainly because none of that existed before 400 AD and as long time
listeners know, that's when I lose interest in the world.
We're also not and a bunch of people may tune in.
now. This is also not going to be how to get yourself ordained. Oh man, I can't
just go on to UniversalLifeTurch.com and well, you can man, shaman, pose or something
like that. And that'll be worth the paper it's printed on. You will be able to
perform weddings in Pennsylvania. I think that is true. Or dainty online like that.
So especially if you're planning on doing weddings in Pennsylvania, not the
road to take. But we're not going to
you what the road to take is because that's not what the episode's about. What we are talking about is
or nation itself or nation is a right as a ritual as a sacrament as a mystery of the church.
And obviously that directly relates to priesthood, especially as we get started, a lot of what we're
We're going to be talking about tonight is going to grow out of
Aaron and his sons.
Yeah.
Aaron is the first high priest.
His sons is priests.
The other Levites.
These are the first folks who get ordained in the scriptures.
And we have a lot of detail of how exactly that happened.
Yeah, we're going to go over that.
It's deeply weird, you guys.
So in great detail.
There will be, you know, the fatty portions above the kidneys.
They're coming.
We're flying through the...
And also prehistoric bacon buns.
Just putting that out there.
It's true.
All you Lithuanian Americans know what I'm talking about.
So this actual ritual, what is being done to someone when they get ordained, when a man
gets ordained, what is being done to them?
And so that means...
that our discussion is going to sort of start.
One of the reasons we're starting with Aaron and his sons,
sort of, there's gonna be a little preface.
But is that in order to have an ordination right,
you have to have a formal priesthood as such.
Yeah, because you have to be being ordained into
something. Right. So one of the things we really emphasized on the priesthood episode
was that before the little bitical priesthood, before the priesthood of Aaron, that the
priestly role was a role played by the father or the head of the household, or the head
of a clan or the head of a tribe, right, that it was a role within a family structure.
rather than this man here is a priest.
Yeah.
This other man over here is not a priest.
It's just, you know, it's, it's just what dad does.
Right.
And so that requires a priesthood, right, as such,
not just a concept of the priest or the role
of offering sacrifice, but an actual priesthood.
so that
the ordination is making a person who previously was not one of those into one of those.
And we probably should mention now, even though we haven't talked about this before, but what
has that ever stopped me from springing things on Father Andrew? So this series, as was mentioned,
and this sort of our series on the sacraments
or mysteries of the church.
And this is one that our Protestant friends,
well, you can never say all Protestants,
but this is almost all at least.
Don't see ordination as a sacrament.
Yeah, right.
I think for even the ones that do see things as sacraments,
because a lot of Protestants don't see anything
as a sacrament,
There's just...
baptism in the Eucharist, you know, for a lot of them it's just those two and everything else is not.
And if you're a Lutheran you kind of have absolution.
Right.
It's the one.
I don't think it's a prep for often.
But yeah, or a day should is not.
That said, that said, and we'll talk about this a little more later on,
There is actually though.
Many of our Protestant friends would be loathed to call it a ritual.
There is actually ritual attached to them sitting apart somebody to ordained office.
Yeah, right.
There's often laying on of hand.
Right.
I mean, that's a thing that is being done in a lot of cases.
Yeah.
And later on tonight, we're going to talk about the difference in how or nation is seen,
which is really a difference in how the sacraments in general are seen.
that are probably, or least hopefully, will kind of make plain why you would have Protestant groups
who are doing something that looks a lot like a right of ordination but not wanting to call it a
sacrament. But we will get to that as we move on. The night is young. Yeah. So
As we were mentioning, the priesthood starts out as just a function, and this is sort of
quick review of that other episode, a function of fatherhood.
And fatherhood broadly considered, because we're not talking about nuclear families.
Nuclear families are what families get whittled down to in the industrial revolution in urbanization.
But we're talking about broad extended families,
clans, tribes, think of Abraham and his wife and later on
children and servants and Herzmann and his nephew
Lot and Lot's family and Herzmann and the big extended
family.
And there is someone who had the patriarchal role
and put
tree, our key is just the first father or the highest father or the right sort of the
father of the whole, right?
And that was the one who was offering sacrifices for the family.
And we see that with Abraham.
We see that with Isaac.
We see that with Jacob.
We see that with Job.
Yeah.
Right.
And there's also, as we talked about, as you see,
start to get groups of tribes and clans in Israel. So this really starts in Egypt.
Right. As that grows from sort of one big extended family in the second two thirds
of the book of Genesis into nations. So you have tribes, clans within the tribes, families
within the clans, right?
You have that evolves into eldership, right?
where the person who has that patriarchal role in a given family is then part of a group
of leaders within a clan, right, and then groups of leaders in the tribe.
So you get the elders of the people.
And as we also talked about in that previous episode about priesthood until the time of the
golden calf, right, those are the ones who were still offering sacrifices, which means there
There was it. There was.
wasn't during that period until we get to the tabernacle and Aaron and his sons, there wasn't just
this single sanctuary, this single place where sacrifices were offered. Yeah, it was just something
that was done within either the precincts of the family or the larger family unit or whatever.
There wasn't like a temple or a tabernacle or a shrine, you know, that everybody went to.
Right, and when we're dealing with no ads like we see in the patriarchal nerds
in Genesis, they're building altars in particular places and offering sacrifice there.
So when these things happen, that we described in that episode, where the priesthood is taken away
from Moses and given to Aaron, and it's taken away from the elders as a group and given to the
the Levites in particular at the time of the Golden Calf.
There is this shift, right? So the, there is a split between fatherhood and
eldership and a particular kind of priesthood. Okay, so what kind is that? Right?
Well, the specifically the sacrificial priesthood. Yeah, okay. Yeah, because
are still like a pretty small role of intercess.
for instance, right, and leadership and these other things. Yeah, right, right. Right. And Moses
maintains the leadership of the people, right. And we talked to that previous episode, that's why
you have a separate king and high priest, right? John here, canis accepted. After that, right? Those
two things are are split and spoilers for the end of that episode. Those come back together, right?
It's incredible.
But so the elders of the tribes are no longer performing that priestly function.
That priestly function is given over to the Levites.
And Aaronus I prized his sons as priests, their descendants as priests.
The Levites, the other Levites assisting them are now playing the role for the other tribes.
tribes in relation to the other tribes that previous
the leadership within each tribe played for that tribe,
sacrificially. Right? Right. And so that move is also what produces
the single sanctuary. Right? That the Levites now who are doing this
for everyone, there's not going to be a separate shrine and a separate altar
alter in the territory of e
of the tribes because the Levites are doing or there wasn't supposed to be, we'll put it
that way. Right. See, Bethel had gotten their calves and that kind of thing happened. See
Jeroboam. Yeah, right. Right. But the the concept within the Torah, shall we say, that there
there should be this one, this one alter
where sacrifice was offered to you.
away is connected to the idea that there's one high priest and one central priesthood,
right connected to it. These things go hand in hand. So before we just did all this building
up to Aaron but before we can get into Aaron we have to do that preface. We have to roll
back a little bit as is our want.
to actually all the way to Adam.
Oh, all the way to Adam, that's a surprise.
Yeah, that's...
So, and this is, again, a reminder of some things we've already talked about on the
show, but one of the things that's going on in Genesis with Adam is that Adam is used,
the model for...
priesthood. Right. He is from the perspective of Moses where the priesthood is being instituted,
right? Adam represents a prototype. Yeah, although not like ordained. Right. There was not a
ceremony. He was not, so for example, he was the only dude. So it was not him instead of some other
non-existent person. Right? Exactly.
And then when we see like we see Canaan Abel offering sacrifices, but there's not a, you know, it's not Father Canaan brother Abel, you know, right, right. They both do it. Right. Right. Right. Right. It's not Adam offering it. Right on their behalf. But so, but Adam is, and this is one of the important details in the text of Genesis that often gets overlooked. Adam is created from the ground and then taken and placed in Eden.
So there is a sense where even Adam, even though he's not called out of a massive people,
right?
He is taken out of the world and put into this holy place, which is what sanctuary literally
means, right?
Put into this holy place, this walled garden paradise, which is the place where God is,
where God dwells, right?
to serve and we've talked about before.
I know in multiple episodes of the show how Genesis 1 follows this structure of the building of a temple
in the ancient Near East, and we've talked at least a couple of times about the way in which
Adam's creation in Genesis 2 sort of inverts the typical ending of that story, where the culmination
of that story in the...
ancient Near East, usually after a bunch of people have gotten killed and their blood has purged the
dedicated sanctuary
But the enemies of the God and all this kind of thing. But at the at the end of
That story of the building and consecration of sanctuary the last step is that the image of the God is placed in the
sanctuary. Yeah, and the rituals performed
to open its mouth or its nostrils depending on.
What you're reading so that the spirit of the God can come in and dwell in it and it
becomes sort of a hypostasis of the God.
Yeah.
And see the idolatry episode for all of this.
In writer detail if you're interested.
And then now, right, you've got the God there in the temple and it can be, you know,
fed, watered, washed, clothed, right by people, and in
turn, if the rituals are performed correctly, it will hypothetically do things for you like allow
you to have children and give you good crop yields. And this is part of the, yeah, part of the
basic Jewish critique here is, okay, so it can't wash itself or dress itself, but it could give you crops
and children. Right. Yeah. There's a flaw here. Right. That's why there's just so much anti-idology
smack talk in the scriptures.
Yeah, it tips over and you have to set it back up. Yeah
And so Adam is
Right the reverse of that God makes Adam as his image
Right rather than Adam making an image of Yahweh the God of Israel to use
instrumentally
God makes
Adam and breathe the spirit into his
is nostrils.
right and places him in the sanctuary as his image.
And so that placement, right, that in liveening that placement in the sanctuary
effectively is Adam's ordination. That may seem like a super big stretch right
now. But by the end of the episode, right?
as we go forward and look at Aaron and ultimately Christ I think this will start to fit together.
Yeah, stick with us everybody.
Yeah, it's a lot of road getting from there to here.
Anyway, so when we see Aaron as the high priest, right,
We're immediately greeted by this imagery.
that is deliberately evocative of paradise and of ad...
Right, in parade.
I mean, it's worth pointing out that the tabernacle first
and then, of course, later the temple is not four bear walls
and a sermon.
It's got a whole lot of stuff that's supposed to remind you of Eden.
In fact, there'd be kind of no point of preaching a sermon in there
they'd be like maybe one of their priests.
Right. That's true. No one goes in there except to appreciate it. That's true. Yeah. Yeah.
Don't push my analogy too far. Come on. Okay. Sorry. Sorry. It's the four bear walls
that I was really kind of trying to emphasize. Okay. Okay. Those are bear walls. Yeah. Okay.
Right. Right. You have in the tabernacle you have the embroidered
cherubim. You have the sculpted
uh... care of him on the arc of the covenant
right who are the throne guardians
Yeah, you got it.
Have it.
Pomegranates, greenery, foliage.
Yes.
Yeah, especially in the temple, the fruit trees, the imagery of the fruit trees.
And remember, you know, there's the the cherub, the carav with the flaming sword at the gates
of paradise, right?
So these, this is all of this imagery.
Yeah.
Which gets carried over into modern Orthodox churches, by the way, everybody.
Just about everything we mention gets used in Orthodox churches including the
the fruit and the vines and all that kind of greenery stuff.
Right.
And the priests and the high priest especially,
right, the whole purpose of them being consecrated and offering the sin offerings for themselves
and for the people and all of this is to allow them to enter in.
Yeah.
Right. So reentry into paradise is a basic element, right?
this. They're going to come into the presence of God into the place where God dwells back into paradise,
right, from which Adam had been cast out, right. And we see the same kind of pattern in terms of the
The high priest is taken as Aaron, right, is one of the people, right, but this is his brother, and he's taken and he...
is made the high priest and placed in the sanctuary.
And as we said, there'll be great deal of detail
about that later on, right?
And that placement, right, constitutes his ordination
that we're going to read about.
And he's now there as the image of God,
and we'll get in the
that more in a minute. And so the high priest is set up as a new atom, right, who is now going to
re-enter only tentatively, only really enter in once a year to the most solely place, right?
and always with you know
with blood to purify with offerings for his own sins and those are the people. All that stuff
Hebrews talks about. Yeah, I mean, it's all this sense of there's the loss of paradise and so
there's this kind of temporary approaching and entering and approaching, you know, like it's
sort of trying to get back to paradise is what's happening in the Tabernacle on Temple.
Right? And the Hebrew thing is important, right? Because there's good...
be a running theme through this episode.
It's the people off now.
They're probably several, but one of them is going to be that a lot of times we're missing
huge swaths of stuff in the scriptures because we're so obsessed with, in particular, our
atonement theories. Right, so...
If you hear someone discuss Christ is the great high priest in Hebrews,
I'll go ahead and say nine times out of ten eight times out of ten may be more fair, but you get the point
they'll be talking about
Atonement Christ making atonement. How does it work? How does Christ make atonement? Right? Right?
and
first and foremost
They're missing this imagery that connects Christ as
great high priest and Christ as new Adam. Yeah. And the return to paradise. A lot more complex
in depth going on and all of this. Right. And not an image of paradise made with human hands on
earth like the tabernacle and the temple, but actual paradise, the actual presence of God
in the heavenly places as he said. So there are going to be several places here.
right what
where we're going to ultimately be connecting some of these things to Christ's fulfillment,
right?
Where that fulfillment is obscured by this focus on this or that atonement theory, trying
to prove it over against other ones and that kind of thing.
So while that will come up several times in the episode, we're not talking about atonement
this episode.
that episode too.
So we're going to set that aside and try to look at all these other things that we might
miss if we're focused on that tonight.
So Aaron then is this pattern of a new Adam, an outline, a suggestion, a shadow.
This is the kind of language that the New Testament uses.
And then Christ comes and fulfills that.
Right, fills it in.
fills it up to overflowing.
And is the new Adam in a truer sense? Is the high priest in a truer sense? And those in some sense
mean kind of the same thing. Yeah, all of those things, including Adam himself, are ultimately
pointing towards Christ, who is all of it. Yeah. And so more.
So one
of the stories about Aaron, that gets referenced a lot. It gets referenced a lot in our Orthodox
liturgics. It gets referenced a lot in when people are talking about the ruin your Sunday
school. Quote unquote, the contents of the arc of the covenant. Oh, it's so hard to remember
that stuff.
So the you may have been taught in Sunday school that there were three things in the arc
of the covenant.
Well technically four, but one of them is a set of two things.
A jar of mana, the two tablets of the covenant and Aaron's rod that budded.
Sure.
Right.
Not actually.
Not true.
The only thing
in the arc where the two tablets of the law, two tablets of the covenant, which, as I
already previously wrote in your Sunday school, are two copies of the same thing.
Yes.
And also you take the cover off and you put your hand in there and there's a little of
dust.
It'll melt your face off.
That is true.
I saw it happen.
of newsreel footage to some Germans who seemed like pretty.
nasty people. They said it was beautiful, but no. Not 19th century Germans. Yeah. Early 20th century
German. Early 20th century Germans. Mid 20th century Germans. V worst kind. So the, the, but so the
other two things, Aaron's rod that budded that we're about to talk about more and the jar of manna
were kept in the sanctuary in the most holy place.
Okay, so they're kind of nearby near the Ark of the covenant near the Ark. Yeah, right. They were the contents of the Holy of Holies
Not the Ark itself
Also
Just because I know I mentioned this in an old episode, but God did not live inside the Ark of the Covenant
It was his footstool. That's true
Yeah
It's not his little house
So all all these references to Aaron's rod that budded or the budding of Aaron's rod which designate
it the priest, right? Yes, that's in the canon. That's the controversy is of the canon of the cross actually.
Right. Is all referring to a story that's in numbers 17. And people don't read the book of numbers a lot.
But I think if most people made a Torah tier list, numbers would...
be five out of five, right?
It'll be the lowest on the list.
Probably tier list for a lot of people.
I don't know why you would make a Torah tier list.
I mean, it's all of a piece.
Yeah, yeah.
And I'm assuming that you can't assign multiple books
to the same tier, which would be hard.
Cause like, let's face it, Genesis and Exodus both S tier.
But you get the point.
Numbers is not the not people
favorite book to read. People usually don't even get there because somewhere in Leviticus
they lose interest. Right. They lose track of all the butchering instructions and how
to deal with mildew and stuff. Yeah. And if they were thinking about skipping ahead to
numbers, they saw some genealogies and punch right out. Right. But there's narrative in
numbers people. There's narrative. Yes. Yes. And numbers 17, shockingly, comes right after
number 16 and
We talked about numbers 16 at a couple of points in the priesthood episode.
I believe in another episode where we talked about the sons of Kora.
Yeah, this is the Kora rebellion.
I think we talked about it in one of the episodes where we talked about the underworld.
Yeah.
Because they get sucked down into Hades.
Cheels.
Right.
But we haven't really talked about number 17, which is in the aftermath of that.
And understanding that it's in the aftermath of that is sort of key to understanding
what's going on?
going on. You won't believe what happens next. So, so there had just been just a really
briefly summarized, right? At this point, Aaron is already the high priest. He's been ordained
as the high priest. He's offering sacrifices. That happened back in Leviticus. We're going
go back. And that's why Cora and company are complaining because they're like, hey.
What makes him so special?
Are we all priests?
Yeah, we all believers.
Are we all school?
Yes, it's not all of Israel holy.
Right?
Are we not holy?
Why is he lording it over us?
Right.
So, yeah, democracy finds its beginning.
Anyway, I have over Korra.
All the way with Korra.
Yeah, I'm not.
So Aaron's already the high priest, right?
And there's already been, but there's been this challenge, right?
And when you read what Kora says, it kind of veers back and forth between Kora thinks Kora
ought to be the high priest or barring that we just shouldn't have one.
Right.
Priesthood of all believers.
Or at least the heads of all the clients because he was the head of a client.
Yeah, right.
Yeah, the old status.
He was a conservative.
So in the British sense.
Yeah.
So this story in number 17 is about God making a public testimony, a public affirmation
right and an ongoing public affirmation that he had made, he had given the priest
to Aaron. Yeah. And the way this works in case it's been a while since you read number 17
is God tells Moses, you know, talk to the heads of all of the the the the
talked all the chiefs and get their the tribes the tribes. Yeah, the the head of the tribes
get their 12 staffs together because they've each got one as this sort of symbol of authority,
Right. The rod. Yeah. The rod. Yeah. And then line them all up.
in the, in the, the Tabernacle, right? I'm trying to, yeah, in the tent of meeting, yes,
the Tabernacle, right? And, and then God says, I'm going to cause one of these staffs to
sprout. And they will have a detail I left out, write everybody's name on their staff, right?
So we know who's the, who's, you know, and he's going to cause one of them to bud and
And that will prove that God has chosen that man to be priest.
So it's...
This one buts out of all the 12 and that proves it.
And of course, it's Aaron's.
Aaron's is the one that actually begins to sprout.
Right, right.
And Moses is reminded to put Aaron's name
on the staff of Levi, not his own.
Yeah, right.
Sorry, Moses, you know, right?
Because there's another piece of that
the priesthood having been taken away from him.
Yeah.
And in the ESV, it says it sprouted forth fresh almonds.
That sounds just delightful.
But um...
So, right. So, this rod buds to new life. And then that budded rod is taken and it's put
into the sanctuary to be this continuing, ongoing testimony to the fact that it's Aaron
and Aaron's line.
Yeah, right. Who has as a kind of relic to prove the thing that happened right to to
So it literally says at number 17 when God says why he's doing it.
He's like, I'm saying this to stop the grumbling so that they will stop grumbling.
Like the word grumbling appears like three times in one sentence.
Right?
Just like no more of this, right?
This is going to be settled once and for all and you're going to have this symbol.
But so that the question is why this particular symbol?
Right?
I mean, God could have just spoken with a loud thunderous voice.
it said Aaron.
is the high priest, right? Like there's, right? You know, there are any number of things God
could have done. Why does he choose this particular thing? Right. And so the rod and the
reason why it's important that it's the rod is that the rod is the symbol of judgment.
Right. And this is judgment in the sense that we've always talked about it on the podcast.
Right. Right. Not judgment in the sense of condemning people. It's not the rod you use
to beat people.
death when they're putting things in order, putting things in their right arrangement,
putting things out of whack back into whack, right? So in whack. And sometimes you do that by
whacking some, no. So the rod remember is what's used to send the plagues upon Egypt. The rod is
what is used to split the the red
right? That makes the water come out of the rock. Right. Also held up, you know, to defeat
Amolec. Right. Yeah. So, tons of broad action. This rod is that symbol, right? I'm sort
of, or the restoration of order, of good order, right? But a rod is also a dead piece of wood.
Right. It's not alive. Right. Right. Um, and so a rod.
budding, right, combines that order, that restoration of order, that judgment, that restoration
of justice with the blossoming forth of new life. And so this is Edenic imagery, right?
So we've talked before, fill the earth and so do it, right? The two commandments to Adam
or to continue God's work of creation.
right to establish order and fill it with life.
And man and woman cooperate to do that. So the staff, the priest,
right, with the priest with the budded rod, right? This is the one
through whom God is working to continue his work of establishing order and bringing forth new life.
Right?
So...
Everybody, all those other elders from the other tribes, still had their authority in terms of order,
right, in terms of governance, in terms of red-ring judgment, and establishing justice within
their tribes and clans, right? But they did not have this special priestly authority that Aaron had,
that allowed it to bring forth life to fill
that order. To make things idanic again. And here's the piece that again, sometimes
missed because we're obsessed with our Atonement theories, as you mentioned, this is in the
kind of a see of the the cross. And especially in St. John's Gospel, Christ repeatedly
refers to his crucifixion.
and the narrator, St. John, refers to Christ's crucifixion
as when he is going to be glorified.
Yeah, this is the hour.
When he is going to be revealed,
when he is going to be glorified.
And so the cross, right,
the dead would of the cross that blossoms forth
through Christ's death and resurrection with new life
is what marks him out as the great high priest.
as the new Adam. And so when we're writing hymns about the cross, right, this is not just, like Nietzsche
said, oh, here's a stick of wood in the Bible. Let's say it's the cross, right? Because there's more
connections to just these things are both wood, right? Have a little imagination there for you to
Come on.
We uh...
but that the cross becomes this symbol and this marker ongoing in the same way that the
rod was kept in the sanctuary. The blossoming rod was kept in the sanctuary as this ongoing
testimony to of to whom God gave the high priesthood. The cross as symbol now becomes the ongoing
testimony of the identity of Jesus as the Christ as the Messiah. Yeah, which is part of why we display it
everywhere. Right. And St. Paul meditates a lot on how that's an inversion because for your
average Jewish person at that time, getting crucified by the Romans was the mark that you
were a false Messiah. Yeah. And literally at the very, very, very, very bottom of society.
Yeah. Like that's what happened. When a guy claimed up, showed up and claimed to be the
Messiah and he wasn't the Messiah the Romans crucified him that's what happened.
Yeah, right. Right. And this is why where he gets into the right, it's a scandal for the Jewish
version. It's foolishness to the Greeks, right? That it has been, this one's been inverted in
this way. But if we understand what's going on with Aaron in number 17, then we should also understand
and what's going on with the cross.
And this is why Christ is always kind of chastising the authorities and the scribes and
stuff who come against him.
If you guys really understood Moses who you're reading all the time, you'd get this,
right?
So the...
But they don't.
Yeah.
Well, some did.
Yeah, some believed.
Yeah.
Some did. Some believed.
Yeah. And so Aaron, his son's the Levites.
at this point are being sort of permanently designated to this, that particular altar,
that particular ministry, right, that particular sense of priesthood.
And it's also important here that priesthood is repeatedly characterized as a gift.
Yeah, it's not something that Aaron got because he was the best, because he's got it achievement.
Yeah, he and his sons accomplished some great act.
Right or it's in a
or right, he was just the smartest guy in Israel,
or he was the holiest guy in Israel.
Yeah.
Or, right, there is, none of that.
It's given to him as a gift, right?
And his sons and grandsons and great grandsons
are whoever happens to be born into that line
and some of them we're gonna see later are near to Wells.
Some of them are right.
men and some of them are wicked men. But they still have this gift that they're then going to be
held responsible for how they use. So our last big element here in terms of Aaron and the high priest in
general going forward and Israel being presented as a new Adam, right, as the image of God.
God as the one who images God is two image God comes in taking a look at his
vestments. Yeah, which is pretty involved. If you look at the actual scriptural
passages, this isn't just, you know, we're a nice suit Aaron. The
repy suit. Those are the vestments of the Baptist preachers that I grew up
listening to. Nice set of clean clothes. Yeah. Yeah. Right. Yeah. So there
specific vestments before we're done tonight we're going to get into even how
those vestments were consecrated and treated. But for now we just want to talk
about the vestments themselves and those are described twice in the book of
Exodus. The second half of the book of Exodus is everything twice. And frankly
sometimes people don't even get to Leviticus because the second time they
read about what kind of goat
here was used for the tabernacle panels.
They punch out, right?
And the reason everything gets repeated is,
first everything gets described.
Here's how you're to make everything related
to the tabernacle.
And then they describe making everything
for the tabernacle exactly according to those plans.
And so it's just a repeat, right?
Yeah.
And so the vestments of the high priest
are in Exodus 28 and Exodus 39.
Okay.
And you can go to either of those places because it's a repeat.
And the sort of overall pattern, as I know we've mentioned, I don't think we
went into a lot of detail on it before, but we mentioned before is that the
vestments for the high priest are strikingly similar when we read accounts of
the dressing of idols in the ancient Near East, very similar to the way in which
idols were vested. Now how do we know? I mean, so we're looking at like ancient pagan religious texts that describe this kind of thing.
Yes.
Yeah.
And descriptions of just temples and
right.
Right. So, so the high priest of Israel would look to someone in the ancient Ereast like a walking talking idol.
Yes.
Effectively.
You know, one of their idols.
Yes.
Now these
There are also very similar investments to what a priest king in the ancient Near East,
like especially Mesopotamian priest kings, what they would have worn when they were exercising
priestly sacrificial functions, but there's a reason for that, and that's that those priest
kings were actually considered God kings.
Yeah, right right so they were considered a God so yeah
They would be dressed the same way an idol would be dressed because in their
point of view the idols of God, the kings of God, without God's
dress, right? But, right? This is an inversion of that, right? In that Aaron is
not going to be sacrificed to. Yeah, he doesn't receive worship. Right. He has a
a fundamentally different relationship.
he is not a God, right?
He is going to have this imaging role
in the same way that that imaging role was given to Adam
in the first place, right, of serving as the image of God.
And so as we go through here, sort of the elements of those investments,
We'll start to see that in
in more detail. The first, probably the most famous, probably the most famous part of
the vestments is the the E-Fod or E-Fod. But I got how you want to pronounce that.
Oh, sort of breastplate. Well, there's another thing that's sort of that's usually called
the breastplate. Oh, that's true. Yeah. Yeah. Which I mean, so like an E-Fod, I was just
really nothing. Yeah, yeah. I looked this up and you can buy them on eBay. Like you can go look up an
e-Pod and there's not only things that are designed to be like a full-size e-Pod or whatever,
but also you can get like little e-Pod pendants, you know, little chotch geese that are e-Pod-like.
So I can't endorse any of those particular sellers. I don't know if they're, you know, good
with sellers, whatever.
I'm just gonna get darn near anything on eBay.
It's true. It's true. You can buy e-fods on eBay.
There should be, I mean, to get enough of them, enough people selling these things,
they should have their own separate site like e-fod Bay. What's that? What's that?
Bible theme park. Do they have somebody dressed as a high priest walking around?
Oh, man, I bet you they do. Maybe that's where they got to supply those guys.
High priest cosplay. There's got to be somebody going around doing presentations.
Christian schools. Yeah. Yeah. And stuff. You know, like this is how the high-prestress.
Like it's a little minor industry that needs to have EFOD supplied to it. Yeah. Just, you know, it's a business opportunity.
I'm just putting that out there for everybody. So what the EFOD is most famous for though is probably the 12 stones on it.
the 12 precious stones that had 12
symbols on them that represented the 12 tribes. And the, yes, the colors of the stones and
the symbols on them is related to Jewish astrology. Hey, it's Christmas time. We have to talk about
Jewish astrology. That always gets me in the Christmas mood. We mentioned this in our first
Christmas episode, days of your.
And talked about how you get some of this in the testament of Jacob at the end of the book of Genesis where you see this animal imagery.
This prophecies to his 12 sons.
And that was the association of particular tribes with particular constellations in the zodiac.
And so that symbol is
is carried out sort of in the in the stones that are held in the the ephat right but the core
importance of them is not the particularity of each of the twelve right. The the important
element is the weight. Yeah. I mean you know some of these ephats you can get on Amazon and
at the
Holy Land Mall.
Sorry.
You're just obsessed with it.
Just get yourself an e-Pod.
Okay.
Just dying to it.
There's one like the
same guy's with to it.
There's one the chain guy wears it on.
And it looks like flavor.
Flav.
You know, except like it's an e-Pod and
it's of a big clock.
But yeah, there's these,
there's these big pieces of metal.
I mean, so they do look heavy.
Select the weight
thing is I think playing into these modern e-fods that you can become your own high priest,
get yourself an ordination on universities to a high priestly height man.
So what a laugh.
You've gone all the way down this rabbit trip.
I love Bible Kitch.
I'm sorry.
It's just so fun.
But so that that way is important because we're going to be coming back to numbers 18, the
chapter after the
budding of Aaron's rock. We're going to be coming back to that later on. But one of the first
things mentioned there that we're going to develop later this evening is this idea of the
high priest bearing carrying the sins of the people. Yeah. Right.
Into the sanctuary. And so that weight of the stones representing, right, the people
is a part of that.
And the this Eiffah with the stones is part of one element of that imaging and that priestly role of the the priest sort of being the representative of Israel.
Right. He is sort of the summing up of Israel there, representing Israel before God.
So that's that element.
Another reasonably well-known piece of these
restaurants is what's called the breastplate where the
Irm and Thuma were kept.
We've mentioned those before on the show.
No, we don't know how they worked.
Yeah, it doesn't say although once again,
you can buy these things online.
But it's just a total guess though.
what do they look like? What were they? We know they were two stones. We know that when there was
some case where they really couldn't figure out what they should do in terms of the will of God,
they would cast them in some way. Yeah. And they would, they would tell them some people assume
it's some kind of casting lots or something. Yeah. The description just isn't there in the Bible.
Right. So we just we don't know. And but that was.
of the function. And so the Irman Thoma are probably better known than the breastplate
that they were kept in, but they're there. So then there's sort of the main robe
that the high priest would wear, which had bells on it. Okay. And you were overjoyed when I told
you this because this is, I believe it correct me if I wrong, but this is one of the dumbest things I
I think you had heard.
This is one of the dumbest things I think I've heard in my life.
Yes, okay.
I love learning really dumb things that people say seriously.
I don't know.
Right.
It's sort of like linguistic kitsch.
Yeah.
So this, why are there bells on the high priest's rope?
What are the bells for?
Yeah.
I mean, the kind of like urban legend that I had always heard growing up.
was the priest is in there, he's got the bells jingling as long as he's moving around. And if you
hear the bells stop, then that means that God has struck him dead because of something that he did.
And so then you need to pull him out by the rope that's supposedly tied around his ankle,
which by the way is never mentioned anywhere in the Bible.
Right. Yet it's the thing that gets passed out when people say this. Like that's the bit that I was
raised with, which is probably not...
Yeah, there may have that may have been a late like second-templar practice.
Yeah, so it might be a kind of an ancient thing, but again, not mentioned in scripture,
there's no rope tied around the high priest's ankle. But that, even if that is completely wrong,
does pales in comparison to this very dumb thing that you informed me about.
So now everybody else gets to know it. So what little data do you have to do that?
the problem with that from the perspective.
of the text is the text says that in some way these bells are to keep the high priest from dying.
Yeah. Not notify you when he has died. Presumably you could tell that because there'd be a big thump.
Right. So we just doesn't come out after a while. So people scholars, these are
The state of Scotland legit scholars have put this forward.
Okay.
People with doctoral degrees.
People with B.A.
H.D.'s advanced degrees, actual academics.
The sort of folk and jobs who cite what I'm about to tell you is coming from the pea
source very confidently.
They say, pea says what I'm going to tell you.
So I say, well, so what does this mean that the bells are there to in some ways keep
the high priest from dying?
Okay.
Here is what these scholars say.
You're not prepared.
I'm not prepared even here to say the bells are on the high priest garbage.
So that when he goes to go into the sanctuary, God will hear him coming.
Because if he didn't, he came in there disturbed the divine rest unannounced.
God might smite him accidentally.
Yeah, just made sure all those reviews we get where people say there's too much giggling.
It's just as intispec it was just too much.
Yes.
People with pH, people who spent like a decade of their life studying the Bible.
Wow.
In general, and the Torah in particular.
Don't scare God, you guys.
Yes.
Don't startle God.
He might kill you.
And he can't bring you back to life or anything.
Right.
even if you've got some how-did, oopsie, kill someone.
Um, because they woke him up out of a sound sleep.
Um, I know that dissertations have to be written and journal articles have to be published.
But come on guys.
Come on.
This isn't just like some guys, cock eye theory.
People cite this as settled fact.
Wow.
As the teaching of the pea source.
I'm telling you.
Uh, so.
Yes.
Um.
So yeah, once again, I find myself in this weird,
liminal space where I accept most people's critiques of academia,
but I'm also kind of involved in it.
Of course, it's preposterous.
Right?
There's a much simpler read here.
The bells are on the garments to keep the high-priest
A 10
right? Most people who listen to the show are not priests but it is possible for a priest to kind of go into automatic mode and do things by
wrote. Yeah, it is possible to zone out a little bit. Yes, to zone out and lose focus just like with any other human activity. Right.
And so the bells, if every time you moved, there was a bell chime.
Right. There was some kind of chiming sound or rattling sound or something, right? That would help keep you attentive and focused and keep you on task, right?
And if you're in the presence of God, that can be the difference between living and death by holiness.
Yeah.
Right.
And it's a continuation of this by the way that causes our bishops.
to still have bells on their vestments.
It's true.
Though I have often joked that it's to keep them from sneaking up and ordaining you.
But I don't think ordination by stealth actually happens that much.
Yeah.
So then one of the most important elements of the high-prease vestments is what's called
the die of them.
And that sort of a crown, it had a metal band and then sort of in the front had a plate.
And on the plate was written the name Yahweh.
And so this is sort of the other half of the ephod, right?
If the eFOD shows us the high priest representing the people
to Yahweh, having the name of Yahweh inscribed on the Diedem was a part of the high priest
representing Yahweh, the God of Israel, to the people. To the people of Israel, right? This
mediatorial role that he's that he's playing. And it also served as a reminder to the people.
that Israel is a whole bore the name of Yahweh. And so the people as a whole, the people
as a call activity had a responsibility to image who God is to the nations, right, to the
world. In the same way that the high priest did to them, because again, the high priest
to sort of this summing up in one place of Israel.
Right?
Right. And so this, of course, once again, right, finds its fulfillment is filled full, is filled out in
the person of Christ as the great high priest because Christ, of course, is the perfect
representation of Yahweh, the God of Israel, the express image. Right. Yeah. And all the other
language, that's St. Paul and the rest of the New Testament uses, right. So he represents
God perfectly.
to the world and he represents the world perfectly right the people perfectly to God why as Hebrew says
because he also came to share in our humanity right any carry is our sins right you know he does
these two things perfectly and then the bishop who wears vestments who we've already commented on a
a little bit here that are very similar to the high
priests, vestments, and even gets called chief priest or high priest, right?
Is the image of Christ. He has vested that way to serve as the image of Christ in
the midst of his people, and as a responsibility of representing Christ to us being
the image of Christ, and representing us to Christ, as he shares in Christ priesthood.
Yeah, yeah, so...
It's all summed up in Christ, and then the Bishop is the one who is an image of Christ within the context of the Church.
Alright, well, that ends the first half of this episode of The Lord of Spirits.
We're going to take a quick break, and we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young will be back in a moment.
to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-234-7.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Big in Heaven.
A collection of short stories available now on the Ancient Faith Bookstore.
Sometimes poignant, sometimes funny, sometimes heartbreaking, sometimes convicting.
These stories of life in an inner city immigrant Orthodox parish are guaranteed to shake your assumptions
and make you see your
life and faith in a new way.
They are not for the faint of heart,
but they are very much for all who want to embrace
the truth more fully.
And you didn't have to ask Rusk over for help.
Cleaning, polishing, carrying in or out,
any work in the church, the woman was a stalled,
a talloddish you could count on.
No one knew her suffering.
They never bothered to look into her eyes.
surprised me.
Most of the church folks at St. Alexander the
Rolling Dirted Parish didn't even know her name.
It wasn't anything they thought about.
To find this book and others like it,
you can go to store.enginefei.com.
Again, that is store.enginefei.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Steve
and the Young.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-855-855.
2, 3, 4, 6.
That's 855 AF radio.
Thanks for watching Steve.
Again, if you have questions about ordination, in particular, you can call it 855 AF radio.
So here we are. It's the second half of Lord of Spirits.
We just wrapped up talking about the vestments of Aaron and the hybrists that followed him.
So, what's next, Father?
I should say I will also accept.
Any and all questions about the ordination of Aaron the Kalamazoo Michigan punk rock band?
Oh, is that really the name of a Kalamazoo punk rock band?
It was indeed.
Wow.
Western Michigan so surprising.
Full of Dutch glory.
True.
There are damnics up there by the way.
I won't out them by name, but actual close relatives of mine living in Western Michigan.
you
Well, the last name is Damick.
It's true.
So you kind of have.
That's true.
Well, if you run into someone up there, that's named Damick.
It's probably a relative of mine.
Not too far from Kalamazoo, in fact.
So now I'm going to guess.
No, I won't guess.
So we don't eat people tracking them down and asking, no.
I was poor people.
They would have no idea what you're talking about.
Yeah.
What does father Stephen Damick Young say about this?
Anyway.
Yeah. Oh, well, I picture father Stephen Damick Young.
Have you ever seen the composite Superman?
Maybe. Sort of this weird silver age comic book villain who like his left side is Superman
and his right side is bow.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, they're both green for green skinned for no apparent reason.
Right. Yeah. So this is sort of a chimera kind of. Yeah. Right. So I'm picturing
father, uh, father Stephen Daymak young as just half of each of us
like welded together in green. That would be deeply weird because even, I mean, number one,
you're two inches taller than I am, which is not a lot, but enough.
But we have very different.
shapes. It's true. So, it's weird. Some of our good online folks though are
going to meme this now. I know. Thanks a lot. They're going to photoshop this
together. And I at least am going to enjoy it. Just make it green people if it's
going to be canonical. It's skin has to be green like the composite superman.
So yes.
Unless someone is called in while we were just talking about the Kalamazoo Michigan pumpkin punk. No
We'll go ahead and move on to St. D. Nisius the area apagate
Because we can the original area apagate. Yes, so
St. D. Nisius is of course
for us Orthodox folk, Saint Dionysius.
In the West he's more commonly known as pseudo-Dienesias.
Or, for people who don't know the difference between his name and the name of the Greek
God, pseudo-Dionisus.
But don't do that, because there's an Eoda.
There's one Eoda of difference between the two.
So there's Sudo Dionysius and his works.
have a long and somewhat sorted history in the West. They were read and interpreted in
a particular way. We have in the past referenced St. Dionysius in regards to two works of his
that go together, the celestial hierarchy and the ecclesiastical hierarchy. And usually,
We've been coming at it from the angle of...
talking about angels, which he talks about the ranks of angels in his celestial hierarchy.
And then we've sort of used some elements of the ecclesiastical hierarchy, which he parallels
with it to help us understand the celestial hierarchy and understand certain things about angels.
Tonight we're going to use him in the reverse direction.
So we're going to take some of the things we've talked about about angels and our understanding
of how he talks about...
out the nine ranks of angels and apply those to the understanding of ordained office within
the church, which is what he talks about in the ecclesiastical hierarchy.
So part of what we have to do, unfortunately, because we're talking to all kinds of folks,
some of whom have never heard of St.D. Aniseas, some of whom have been pseudo-D. Aniseas,
Who am I?
a very bad impression of him, so whom maybe you have a good impression of him.
It's talk a little bit about who he is and why what he has to say is important.
Yeah, right.
I mean, the base reference, of course, is from the Scriptures that there is a Deneasias
who hears St. Paul preach on the area of apagus and is converted to Christ as a result of hearing
of hearing that preaching does he is called geniuses, the air.
apricot. Right. And the scriptural figure here. Right. And that saint is the second bishop of Athens.
Yeah. I think isn't Athena Goraus is the first? That was here at theos. Anyway.
Here at theos. Okay. Excuse me. Yeah. Yeah. When those multicellabic deck tillic Greek names.
But so there is
that figure with its scripture and the early history of the church, the author of the works
that we're talking about, the celestial hierarchy, the ecclesiastical hierarchy, and some others
like the divine names, right as that person. And I'm expressing it that way because that's something
everyone can agree to.
Right. We can all agree he writes as that person. So then there are folks who argue these
works were written by that person. Sure. In the first century AD. Okay. There are, there's
almost no one in the West who does that for the last six or seven hundred years.
right. Yeah but there's also the idea that you know someone much late
wrote them and then put his name on them. Right, which is what pretty much every
one of the West has said for the last six or seven hundred years. And then within
the Orthodox world, you have sort of versions of this is actually from the
century and this is later but so we have a little different relationship if...
This in fact was written by someone later in that we would still not call him pseudo
Dionysius.
Yeah, because that pseudo idea is this notion that someone is lying.
Right, right, right, right, essentially, right.
And attaching the pseudo in the West historically happened as a way of trying to discredit his
writings because of how they were being used in the West.
So, but it is within the realm, right, of Orthodox belief, that that first century person who's
in the Bible is a saint regardless, right?
Yeah, right.
But it is possible that a later person in the East who was, for example, a monastic who
who had St. Dionysius as his patron saint.
Wrote
as St. Dionysius, his patron,
out as a means of displaying humility.
Essentially not taking credit for his own writings.
Right, he's not trying to lie.
And there's also another possibility,
which is that these writings originated in the first century
and then get added to edited,
or whatever, updated, tweaked, handed down.
Yeah.
much the way scripture did as their
passed down through time. So, right, so that the, in the West, the scholarly and sort of
general consensus now is that they probably date to the fifth century, and were probably
written in Syria.
Of course, this is one of the places where the dissertations have to be written.
Articles have to be published.
Works in our favor because there's a thousand dissenters to that consensus.
As we said before on the show, this is how academia and scholarship is supposed to work.
If there's a consensus, that's a bullseye.
We all need to rip it apart.
It's a consensus.
We must all submit.
And so there's everybody, right, question.
it sort of one way or the other. For my part, I'm not prepared to argue dogmatically that these
were written in the first century, but I will say there are significant elements in St. Dionysius' works
that portray a great familiarity with the details of Greco-Roman.
paganism right which is important to point that out because
You know generally people say the states from the 5th century or maybe even later. I'm not later
But 5th century because that's when quotes for starting up. Yeah
Well by that point paganism and the Roman Empire is
You know kind of last week's news right it's gone. Yeah, frankly gone in a real way
Yeah, so the the texts indicate that whoever wrote them
new things about paganism that
You kind of would need to be there to know.
Yeah, that you wouldn't know at that point, right?
So at least argues for something earlier than that,
or they're being part of the text that's much earlier than the fifth century.
You also have the issue with,
I do not know of a good example.
I'll put it this way.
I do not know of a good example,
even though it's very common in scholarship to
date something to maybe third.
years before the first time it's quoted that we know of, right? I do not know of a case
where that has turned out to be accurate because with something like this, because people
actually people weren't stupid, right? If someone wrote something and then came and said
This is 500 years old.
They didn't...
Right. Right. Right. Right. Right. Right. They do it with something that is shown up recently.
Right. You can just walk into a bishop of the church office one day and say,
behold, I have found the writings of St. Paul's disciple, St. Dionysius. Here they are.
And the bishop would go, wow, this is wonderful. We need to change our theology to match this
because it's so old. I believe you.
right? Like that's not that's not how this ever worked and we have all kinds of
counter examples right where for example you look at the Meritorian cannon right
and when the Meritorian cannon talks about the Shepherd of Hermes it says the
Shepherd of Hermes is not in the New Testament because it was written in our
own day in the middle of the second century right and it says you know
Herb is Pope Pius's brother.
Right?
Like they know who wrote it.
Like they say it was by this guy.
That's why it's not the New Testament.
But it's worth reading.
The mercenary kid is not anti-Shepard of Hermas.
Yeah.
Right?
But they know it was written recently.
So, if people in the fifth century are quoting it as an ancient document, that means it may
not go back to the first century, but it has to go back a good ways before the fifth.
Yeah.
Right?
for them to see
think it was ancient, for the think it was that old.
And one of the big problems about all literature
from that period is that as far as we can tell,
the vast majority of the stuff that was written
in that period in those first few centuries of church life,
it's simply gone.
That's how as far as we can tell, it's gone.
Yeah.
We have lists from ancient libraries of works.
Right.
And they're just gone.
We have less than half of Plato,
we have a tiny fraction of Aristotle.
Yeah, so it's entirely possible that there's whole
world of people quoting things or whatever that just didn't make it.
Just over the vendor You know the necessit to do the history it just didn't get to our time.
Right. Right.
And so, all that is to say,
while you know, it's it's a modern and even a little pre-modern project, right.
The years I gave for the changing consensus is not...
incidental. Has to do with the rise of modernism, has to do with the beginning of the Protestant
Reformation, and the Protestant Reformation trying to weed out what were and weren't authentic
apostolic texts in the West, where there were lots of forgery and stuff, right? So different
standards start getting applied in things. There's more of a suspicion than dubiousness of anything
that claims to be ancient in the West.
And one of the ways that...
tried to discredit something is to historicize it in that way to try and peg it as a late date.
This is why our 19th century German friends were always trying to put the writing of New Testament
books into the second century. Make it as late as possible. And then later on in the 20th century,
you had scholars wanting to try to make the gospel of Thomas a hundred years earlier than it was
written. Right?
because the closer the apostles, you can get it, the older you can make it, the more authoritative.
So I think you don't like, you make late, anything you do like, you make old.
Right? But that's a, that's a, that's a ploy. Right? It's an obvious ploy.
And so even if we have no mention, let's say for the sake of argument, right?
it just for the sake of argument that yes, some Syrian monk.
named Dionysius, wrote all of the writings of St. Dionysius the area of apogite in the fifth century.
That wouldn't change the way in which the church received and has used them
theologically since. Right. Yeah, I mean ultimately it kind of doesn't matter. Exactly when they're
written because the
churches received them in a particular way and been using them all this time.
And it's not been a blip on the radar.
It's been persistent and consistent for centuries upon centuries upon centuries.
Right.
And it's not some fat.
It's not the new thing anymore.
Right.
Even it was the new thing of the fifth century.
It ain't the new thing now.
Right.
Yeah.
So yeah.
So that, that is, again, that's why I don't feel the need to take any kind of
dogmatic stance that no, this must go back to the first
right because ultimately it doesn't matter. Yeah. Um, you know how I feel about dates anyway. Um,
but um, so why did we go into all this about St. Dionysius? Well, the place where the rubber meets
the road on this is how he is read. Right. How we're going to read and interpret St. Dionysius. Um,
And uh...
If you read, if you want the detailed version of this, here's a footnote citation for you.
You could read Lossky's mystical theology of the Eastern Church, where he talks about
the Western and Eastern readings of St. D. D. Nassias among others.
the west, the
northwest has read St. Dionysius as a Neoplatonist. And this was a problem for various
theological reasons that we're going to get into a little bit here for the Protestant
former's and their children in the 17th century.
And so...
So rather than taking a different reading of St. Dionysius, it was discredit these writings
by having them be from another author, having them be late, etc., etc., etc.
You also have to have them be late for him to be a neoplatonist.
Yeah, because neoplatonism doesn't rise in the first century.
Right, right.
So realistically, it's got to be at least third century, first someone, especially someone
it's Syrian to be influenced by Diel.
Platonism. Because you're talking about putinus and porphyry. And why is that important?
The Neoplatinist element. Well, as we mentioned, the two works that we're talking about tonight,
that we've talked about before, the celestial hierarchy and the ecclesiastical hierarchy.
and the hierarchy.
Right? If you're a neoplatinist, right?
Uh, if you have serious, serious case of platobrain, um, means a hierarchy of being.
Ultimately, right? So within Platonism, you have this, uh, polarity between being and becoming.
Okay, that which is in flux that which is changed.
that which is imperfect, that which is impure on the one hand. Yeah, kind of lower. And that which is
eternal, unchanging pure whole, right, on the other. Right. And hierarchies, all hierarchies,
right, are ultimately hierarchies of being in this sense. Right. Because if we're talking about
out of heart.
you have perfection right well then that becomes obvious but if we're talking even about a hierarchy
of like good right purity is better than impurity right that's wholeness is better than lack right
and so what ends up happening and this happens in western theology through the influence of Plato
and the Platonic Period in Western theology which is roughly...
give or take the beginning of the sixth through probably the late 12th early
13th century. You get God, positive at the top of this hierarchy, is pure being
or is being itself. And then everything descending down the hierarchy from God,
Right. Partakes of being, which is God.
in relative degrees, and then also partakes of becoming or lack or these kind of things,
impurity, purely by virtue of not being God.
Right?
And so if you take that kind of idea and apply it to St.
See you next year.
This is celestial hierarchy, for example.
What you essentially get is a sort of nostasis because the ranks of angels become these sort
of emanations of God working their way down to toward humans.
Each one less perfect than the last.
one less pure than the last.
As you work your
way down, but you also get a kind of pantheism, or at least pan-antheism, where the being of
beings, not to go all Heidegger on everybody, but the being of beings becomes God, right?
Which goes further than say St. Augustine, who has plenty plateness.
So, say to Guston would say, everything is good in that it exists.
that existence is good. Right? This is how Anselm's ontological argument works for your real nerds. Right?
Right, but he would not say everything is God in that it exists. Yeah, right. Right.
That's moving from just a kind of Platonism
intoneo-platinism. Yeah right. And that creates a deformed view.
And then if you take that reading of the celestial hierarchy and then parallel it to the ecclesiastical hierarchy,
the hierarchy of offices with ordained offices within the church, right?
Now you're gonna get something really interesting.
Right?
Yeah, I mean what you get is basically that bishops are a different kind of thing.
like an on top.
logically different thing than late. Right. Right. Yeah. Right. And it's also helpful, right, to the west, right?
In particular, because of course, they have a single head of the visible church. Yeah, right. It's
which of your Platonists, right? One. Yes, one, this is always good. One, this is very good. Right.
So you have this one at the peak. Yeah. Yeah. And so.
the grace that Saint Dionysius talks about
Right that that
Distinguishes the levels of this hierarchy gets thought of in these ontological terms
Right these terms of being
right
that and so when we're talking about
ordination
Right, then we're talking about
the person ordained being
into something else, into another kind of thing. Right? And so, and that, even though we may not have
been aware of it, right, before we started maybe on this show for a lot of listeners, when we started
talking about the celestial hierarchy in those terms, you may have thought, well, a cherubim is
is a different thing than a Sarah.
from. No. It's a different thing, right? Well, this is where sort of that rover meets
the road. But we'll get into that more deeply here in a minute. Yeah. Yeah. Cause we actually
have someone calling from Tennessee, I believe. So, uh, or I'm sorry, William, I don't know
where you're calling from. Where are you calling from? Laymarie there. Yes. I am. And it's
volume of Tennessee. You are of tennis, okay?
All right.
Well, all right, but you've worn on a mountaintop.
Well, the greenest dates in land of the free. Yeah, so there you go.
I was raised in the woods, but unfortunately, I do not know every tree. It's very sad.
Did you kill a car when you were three?
I was five actually. Big three things.
Under a blumer. So what's on your mind, William, to see?
So talking about ordination and of being.
sounds like taken and set apart into something else.
I was wondering how that relates to Israel being a nation of priest in Exodus 1956.
Is that like the entire nation of Israel is ordained or the individual people are
ordained? Because to me, it sounds like if Israel is a nation of priest, that requires
some sort of ordination to be given on with either all the individuals or the nation as
a hole or both at the same time.
So, first, is there an ordination going on?
And the nation itself, for all the people are both.
And if so, what is that ordination?
Yeah.
I mean, in this language, right, this idea of a kingdom of priests, a holy nation, this
gets repeated then in the New Testament, to refer to the church as well.
So it's an interesting question.
And I mean, my short answer is going to say no.
They're not ordained to be priests in that sense of an ordained priesthood
But there is something like that going on here, right father
Actually, all right good. Let's have it on actually. I'm gonna say yes
Okay, yes, but also yes
Yes, I mean sort of right they don't go through the stuff that Aaron and Ryan's go right so and as we continue that we're gonna
we're gonna get more into this but there are...
types of priesthood. Yeah, exactly. Right. There are different sorts of priesthood. Right.
And so when it talks about Israel being a kingdom of priesthood, or when St. Peter talks about
the church being a royal priesthood, that's a priesthood in relationship to those to the rest of
the world to those outside. Right? And that has a primarily collective meaning.
So, we're used to as modern people thinking of things very individualistically.
But if we take priest in the sense we've already been talking about it tonight of representing
God to the world and the world to God.
Israel as a whole was called as a whole in their life as a community in keeping the commandments
of the Torah through that communal
life to represent God to the world, to be a light to the nations, right, to the Gentiles.
And they were called in their festivals, probably the best example of this is at the feast of
tabernacles or the feast of booths when they offered the 70 bulls, right, for the 17 nations.
Right, one for each nation, right, to represent the nations to God, right. And so we,
collectively, right, as a church have a royal priesthood that St. Peter talks about, where we as the church and the way we live in community together, the way we love each other.
Right. St. John says, by this all men will know. Right. You love one another.
that we represent who Christ is to the world, and then when we come and we gather and celebrate
the Eucharist, we're...
offering the Eucharist for the life of the world and for its salvation, right? Which is
Christ's sacrifice. So there is a collective level of priesthood there.
Yeah, it's almost like the phrase should rather be rather than being translated like a kingdom of
priests rather, you know, a royal priesthood or even a priestly kingdom. Right. Royal priesthood is
is how
done in Greek. That's why Saint Peter's quote gets translated that way, right? Siding
in Greek. And so a person becomes a part of that priesthood, this is the ordination part,
right? In the old covenant by becoming a part of the people of Israel. So circumcision
eating the Passover and then everything else that goes with that, right? The commandments
the Torah all that. Then the New Testament and we'll see this in particular in the
third half tonight. This is baptism,
presumation that we talked about in the last episode,
that anointing, right, that you enter is in a sense,
an ordination in that you now enter into that collective priesthood.
Does that make sense?
It does.
A follow-up spell.
Sure.
So if the nation itself is sort of.
of the entity is the priestly nation,
an ordination, a priest isn't reordained
every time they serve the divine liturgy.
It seems that there's an event
that's the entrance into the priesthood.
So what is the ordination event for Israel?
Is it the Exodus?
Is it the Ten Commandments?
What's that?
Or is there one?
For the collective,
It would be the
complex of events from Passover to Pentecost that begins with passing through the Red Sea and ends
with the sprinkling of blood at the ratification of the covenant. There you go. Okay. And stay tuned for
the third half. Yeah. I mean, I know it means staying up late, but you know, that's that's the show
you do or yeah, or listen to the recording tomorrow of the third half. That's the case maybe maybe
I don't know your teeth, while your teeth is these.
But yeah, because I know that basically a little odd now, but we're going to get to something
where I think it'll click.
All right.
Thank you.
Thank you very much for calling William of Tennessee.
Okay.
So now that we've said that, and also a lengthy discursus about St. D. D. Neese's The
Area of Apeguide and how one ought to read him.
And don't be a neoplateness.
Yeah.
Don't be a neoplateness.
So yeah.
That was the negative part. The negative part was doby and eoplateness. We're going to come back
here in a little bit to say Dionysius and talk about the better way to read him.
Yeah. Yeah. Like it does all have a point, everybody. It was not just a
yeah, rambling bit of things about Dionysius the area of the good.
One last little bit about neoplatonism also is that, of course,
Neoplatonism was an attempt to make Platonism Christian-ish.
Yeah, whereas the way that it's read a lot of times these days is that Christianity was
Neo-platinized.
Like actually it goes the other way guys.
Right, right.
Yeah.
That is, I mean, porphyry, great platyneus.
Like that's what they were doing, right?
In the same way that nosticism was an attempt to take the status quo ideology of Greco-Roman
paganism and through a
Christian veneer on it. During the early rise of Christianity,
neo-platenism is the same kind of move by, you know, I don't know if
Plutana actually was a member of the Academy. But anyway, by
by Platinum is a by philosophical schools, right, to kind of
try to appeal to the growing Christian market. Right.
don't run after this new Christianity thing, right?
What we've got is still good.
What are the things that are attracting you to Christianity?
Well, we've got those two, right?
There you go.
Or we can make it sound like it at least.
Yeah, so when you see things in very early Christian texts,
and you jump to the conclusion, oh this looks nasty.
Often, that's because it's something that
narcissism took and sort of pirated.
Yeah.
Right.
It's like, if you've only ever heard
ice ice baby, and all of a sudden
someone plays under pressure.
Right.
You might know that.
You're like, oh man.
I know.
Queen and David Bowie, they went and stole
Vittel Ice's sample.
Except I think what is it predated by like
20 years ago like that?
Exactly right.
Perfect analogy. Okay, so I
Didn't know that we'd go to vanilla ice tonight, but here we are that whole bit just clicked for everyone
They know exactly what I'm talking about now. Wow because of that analogy
so
We're gonna go back to the book of numbers
There's gonna be more book of numbers tonight than most people have had in many a year
Now we're going to numbers 8.
18. I said we were going to come back there. This is the chapter after the the rod budding.
And chapter 18 is after the rod buds, then God explains to Aaron what his job is. It's the short version.
It's your very short summary of numbers 18. And the first bit of that, as we already mentioned,
is this idea of bearing
the sins of the people, carrying the sins of the people. Right. And what that means is that he is going to come into the sanctuary. Again, as the representative of Israel, right, a sort of the embodiment of Israel. Right.
He's going to come in with the sins of the people to a tone for the sins of the people.
To make a tone with their, with blood of the...
of atonement to offer the sacrifices, the sin offerings, right? This is going to be his task.
He is going to repent for the people in the sense that he is going to lead them in repentance.
Right. And again, as we're just saying to our caller,
We tend to think very individualistically.
Yeah, right.
We tend to think very individualistically about sin.
Right.
Yeah, you're responsible for your sins.
I'm responsible for mine and it's not my fault.
Right.
And, you know, hey, if I didn't do anything, right, then I don't need a repent of it in this
kind of thing.
Right.
Yeah.
And more than that, right, we being sinful tend to justify ourselves.
You
Well, I did nothing wrong, right?
If you just understood the situation, you would see that I did the only logical, rational,
good thing I could do.
We want to defend ourselves.
We want to rationalize.
We want to justify ourselves, right?
All of these things.
And so part of priestly leadership is leading in repentance.
And sometimes that can literally mean confessing things you didn't do but that the other people did.
Right? He's going and offering sin offerings for the sins of the people.
His own also, but also all the people, all the things. Right?
And he is repenting of them. And he's working to help repent and repentance as we've said,
he's working to help repair the damage.
done. He's leading them in doing that. And that's the core of what it means, right? And acting
that healing, and acting that restoration, taking the leadership role in doing that is what it
means to bear for Aaron to bear these sins, right? So again, right? Sometimes we get it distracted by
by our Atonement theories.
Right?
Yeah.
And.
Isaiah 53 is a passage of the Old Testament where people get very distracted by their atonement theories.
Yeah, that's you know the one where it says Christ borrows sins and you know,
it was bruised or an aggregate, right, all bruised for our niceties, right? The suffering servant passage.
Yeah, right. One of them. Yeah, one of the servant songs, suffering servant, right?
And this turns into a whole thing about penal substitutionary atonement and this and that
And how do we read it, right?
But there is a much more basic
reading of this, once again, that focuses on Christ as high priest. Right? Christ is high
priest. Christ as high priest is the one who leads in repentance as the one who represents
humanity before God. Right? Can lead them in repentance without being guilty of anything
himself. Right. Right. Right. Right. And if we understand that connection, if we understand
this bearing of sins as the role of the high priest, right?
Then what St. Matthew does in Matthew 814 through 17 makes sense.
Yeah, I mean, in that passage, it talks about Jesus healing various people of
different kinds of ailments of a fever, of sicknesses, of demon possession, and
then he references Isaiah and says, thus it was written, you know, he, he borrows
are sins.
and I'm blanking on the exact freezing, but our diseases, right?
Yeah.
He took our tools as a group.
He says, yeah, thus it was fulfilled.
Yes, exactly.
Right.
St. Matthew says it's this fulfilled it when he healed these people.
If you try to make that work, it's a Matthew's gospel
with some kind of atonement theory,
what are you gonna say?
Christ healed someone's fever and he got a fever?
Yeah, or he cast out a demon and beat-
came demon possessed.
Yeah.
It doesn't make sense.
So minimally, that's not how St. Matthew is reading the passage.
Yeah, at the very least.
Right.
The very least St. Matthew is not reading Isaiah 53 that way.
And I think understanding bearing sin as part of the high priestly
role makes sense of how St. Matthew reads it.
And so there's this idea of again
repentance as a collective activity, right? Because going back to the spirits episode, right?
The spirit, you know, sort of animates, motivates a collective, right? And has agency, then
It can sin. It can do evil.
Yeah, right? People do evil as groups.
Right. There is such a thing as systemic evil. Right. There is collective sin. This is,
I don't understand how someone could read the Old Testament prophets and not see this.
Right. Like was every single human in the Northern Kingdom of Israel guilty of all of the
sins that the prophets list and therefore worthy of being destroyed by the Assyrians individually.
You
Right. Right. Was being personally, being personally innocent, give you plot armor where
you could just walk past this area and say we're gutting everyone else. Right? Yeah.
I mean, people suffer for evils committed by other people all the time. Yes. All the tests.
And you can structure your society in a way. You can live as a community in a way that is
evil and that victimizes people.
Yep.
I mean, that's basically human history.
Yes. This is, I mean, this is just abundantly obvious, right?
Until we start speaking theologically,
then we become super individualistic of who's guilty, who's to blame.
Yeah, and the other thing is, like, what is repentance, right?
It's not just, I did a bad thing, and so I'm sorry.
It's about putting things in the proper order.
Like, it's, you know, it's healing things, right?
So someone can do that without being...
personally guilty of having caused the harm, right? So it's possible for a nation
generations after some evil that their ancestors did to repent, which means
that they're putting things in the proper order, they're making right what was
made wrong, even if they're not personally guilty of the evil. I mean we could
also look at it from another direction which is as it says in the description.
if you know to good to do good and you don't do it, that's a sin. You know, that you didn't do good
as a sin. Not just that you did it a bad thing. It's that you didn't do a good thing. That's sin.
Right. And we need to repent to that too. Right. And when you're doing evil as a collective,
you have to repent as a collective and therefore change and transform as a collective. Right. Right.
Right. Right. So if you have a society where everybody at age 30 has to go.
on the run because they get executed.
There's a reference, five people got it anyway.
Yeah.
Then a little hungry father.
You have to dismantle that society and rearrange it.
That's murdering people at a certain age.
If I don't know, you've got a society where for your...
economy to function, you have to have a certain level of unemployment.
And so you have some kind of central bank that deliberately drives up the
unemployment rate for the health of other parts of the economy and
impoverishes people and invigorates them.
At some point you need to do something about that.
That sounds fictional, Father.
Yes, I've just made up two completely unrealistic examples there.
Or cited Logan's run and then another completely
unrealistic example. So this happens at this collective level. And this is part of what we're
talking about with the caller, part of why this collective priesthood is important. Because
one individual.
by himself, cannot show the world,
let alone just a community,
a completely different way to live a communal life.
But a community can.
Yeah.
Right?
A church community that becomes a real family,
and fulfills what due to everything in society,
families are no longer able to fulfill.
right, when that gets fulfilled in the State of Homeland of the Church, that shows the outside world
that there's another way to live and another way to do things. Let's ground it in the love of Christ,
right, and could be transformational. But you can't do that by yourself. This one random individual,
right, he can protest or she can protest what's going on in the community, right, but you can't
Demonstrate.
rate in the way that a community can. So slight
aggression, but not a worthy one, I think. Yeah. So.
So that back to numbers 18. Okay. So then the second part of
numbers 18
gives the other sort of central
And there's actually more ink spent on this than on the sinbearing part.
So this is sort of the main job that Aaron has given in numbers 18 is essentially for
the high priest to serve as a throne guardian.
Yeah, right.
Right.
The idea is that he's going to protect sacred space of the tabernacle in the case of
Aaron later the temple.
Right.
And it's not coincidental, right?
and St. Dionysus Theria Apaguy in the celestial hierarchy, it's the Seraphim and the Cherubim,
the Throne Guardians who are at the top.
Yeah.
parallel to the high priest at the top.
And we actually got recently someone asked this question in our Facebook group.
Why does God need Throne Guardians?
Right?
It's like, like God doesn't need to be protected.
It's not it's it's not God being protected because obviously God does not need to be protected.
You
It's us being protected in a sense from God, not that they're like standing there holding
them back like don't do it, don't do it.
You know, that's not what's going on.
It's that, you know, as humans enter into the presence of God, if we do it in an unworthy
manner, then it destroys us.
So death by holiness.
Death by holiness, right?
So Throne Guardians are there actually to guard us in a sense from the throne, just as
the angel that guards paradise after the expulsion from
paradise of Adam and Eve. They're not guarding paradise from being
solid by Adam and Eve. They're guarding Adam and Eve from destroying
them, some some cells by entering back into paradise.
Right. That's going on. Drawing near to the tree of life. They're keeping them away
from the tree of life so they won't live forever in their evil state.
Yeah. Right. Yeah. And so it's repeated several times in numbers
18. That Aaron and his sons are going to be there. Right. To draw near to
God and so that the other people won't do that and die.
Yeah.
Right. Right. This is the central, this is the central job. And so this, I don't know
if it's just the circles I'm quote unquote, traveling in or if this is on the rise or
if it's just something I've seen a lot lately at random and I'm being anecdote Andy. But
that there has been a lot of
from non-orthodox folk when talking about the Orthodox Church, that something they
don't like about the Orthodox Church is that the Orthodox Church will not just
give the Eucharist to anyone who identifies as a Christian. And often the rejoinder
and this is the correct rejoinder is pointing people to 1 Corinthians 11, 27
through 30 where say Paul talks about...
about the one who approaches it in an unworthy manner,
just eating and drinking judgment
and this is why some of you've gotten sick
and some of you have died.
And so that is the right place to point people.
Right?
But what we can see here in numbers 18
is that this is a primary,
I would say V primary, this is job one,
right, of the priesthood, right?
is.
that the priest is the one through whom people are able to
worthily draw near to God safely,
and that others that need to be protected.
Right?
So, not giving the Eucharist to anyone who I don't know
is approaching in a worthy manner is my primary job as a priest.
Hmm.
not having meetings.
not doing counseling, not leading prayers, less included at coffee hour. What gets called
in the west, in the Protestants are going to fencing the table. That's job one for the
precincts. According to the Bible.
Wow, yeah, and I mean, and there is there is within
the orthodox ordination of a
presber
a priest, there's a part that happens kind of after the ordination proper. The man is already
a priest, but there is an element that happens where after the bread and the wine are consecrated
to become the body and blood of Christ, that the bishop will take that consecrated bread,
the body of Christ and place it in the hands of the newly ordained priest. And we'll say, I'm
I'm going to be paraphrasing a little bit, but he basically says, you know, receive this pledge
and guard it and keep it until the dread day of the second coming of Christ when he will
ask you to give an account for it or something to that effect.
Which has the very big long complicated Greek term, the Pada Kata Thiki, which often gets translated
is that
charge, I think in modern Greek it means something like a deposit. So it's the same kind of idea.
This is a guardianship that's being handed over to this priest. And the guardianship is not,
I mean on the one hand it is, yes, don't let anything harm the body and blood of Christ,
you know, see that it's treated with reverence and so forth. But also it is, as you say,
There's a sense of guardianship of those.
approach it to make sure that they're approaching God in a way that is going to be beneficial for them
and not harmful for them. Right. Right. I don't refuse people,
communion, anyone who wants to, to come into my parish and receive the Eucharist. There are certain
things you're going to have to do first. Right. Right. But you are invited to do those things and
and then receive the Eucharist.
Yeah, so if someone doesn't want to do those things.
that's on them. That's their choice. Yeah. And that's fine. Right. It's your own free will.
If you don't want to do those things, don't do those things. Right. But if you're not willing to
do those things, then I can't give you the Eucharist because it could destroy you. Yeah. So I'm
back into it. You can get sick. You can die. You can be spiritually. But I am here to outline what
what those things are.
For you.
Right.
Show.
Yeah.
So back.
two St. Dionysius.
Dennis.
So St. Dennis.
The Sandini.
Yeah.
I know it is literally the French version, but I don't know.
There's something grander about Dinesias versus Dennis.
Yeah.
Well, Dennis is a menace, right?
So there's that.
So we know it already.
Right there
that this connection between high priest and at the top of the ecclesiastical hierarchy
and Saraphim and Cheribim at the top of the celestial hierarchy is that they have the
same job.
They have the same task, right?
They have the same role.
That is a very different concept.
then them being the same thing, right?
Because objectively they are not the same thing, right?
A seraphim and a bishop are not the same thing.
Right.
He's a human.
What is a seraphim?
Right.
They're not the same thing.
So at the level of being,
This kind of
platonic hierarchy, right? They are not the same thing, they're not parallel in that way.
Nor is there some kind of parallel in a kind of change of being,
right? Sort of as cherubum is to throne so bishops is to
prespitor in terms of what they are. So kind of a analogy of being. That is kind of already
figure out what that would mean, right?
So that that Neal Patanagant interpretation fundamentally falls apart.
Unless right, you want to take St.D. and Icy as completely out of the context of Christianity
and the Scriptures, which seems odd.
So what you have, as we mentioned in St.D. Aniseas is the idea that what...
separates these hierarchies from each other is grace.
And so a lot of what happens between West and East here
and even different parts of the West
has a lot to do with how grace is defined.
So our Eastern reading of Dionysius would be more like
because we understand grace to be the divine energies
meaning divine activity, meaning God working. Right. So for us, this, the, the ecclesiastical hierarchy
and the celestial hierarchy fundamentally mean that God is working through the different
ranks of this hierarchy in different ways. He is doing different things through these
beings, whether they're angelic beings or humans. Yeah, but it's always God doing it. It
God doing it, is God working through them.
Right. And so this is why we could talk about there being kinds of priesthood,
which we already did, right? There's a kind of priesthood that even after the golden calf
that the elders of the people still possessed. But there's also a kind of priesthood,
the sacrificial priesthood that they no longer possessed. Right. Right. Why? God was still working to
to do certain things through the elders of the...
people like justice, right?
To render judgment.
To resolve disputes to keep order, right?
God was still working through those people, just in a different way than he was
working through Aaron and his sons to accomplish different things than he was
accomplishing through Aaron and his sons.
Right.
I mean, yeah, I mean, it's, it's a really important principle.
And I mean, I know I've said this before on the show that every good thing
comes from God.
Everything good that is happening is God doing it.
It doesn't mean that the people who are doing it are not also doing it, but as they do it,
they are participating in God's works.
There's not any independent good.
Right.
So yeah, this is why God can call good works done by humans good, right?
Because they're his works.
Those are his works.
And so just like at creation, he can look at them and call them good.
Oh
When we talk about an ordained priesthood, we're saying that God is working through the ordained man in a particular way.
Right?
Not
that there's this clergy lady divide where God works through the clergy and does not work through the lady.
Yeah.
God works through some people and not through other people. We mean God is working through
and accomplishing things through the clip.
that are different than, it's particular things that are happening through clergy.
And when we talk about that communal priesthood, there are things that God is doing in and through the community as a whole.
Right? That are different than things he does through various individual persons.
Right?
So, this is a sort of critically important distinction, right?
Because the Western read, right, and this is parallel with the Western read of Dionysius,
is that the Western read, at least going into the Protestant Reformation, we should say, right,
that or nation-imparded certain powers and abilities it changed the
character of the human person.
Yeah, it gave part of the
charisma and yes, indelible, indelible mark.
Right.
That this person is now different than he was in an
ontological way.
Yeah, he became a different thing.
Yes, the priest is a different thing.
And then all the way up to, right, the Bishop of Rome is a
different thing.
Right.
Then even because the papacy is a different office than the
Yeah, Pascal.
it for Roman Catholicism. And so at each of those levels there are powers, abilities,
right, music powers in sort of the Aristotelian sense, right, of dynomies, right, that can be
actualized by the person. They can do things, right? So to give just a very, and we'll elaborate
more on this but just to give a very bare bones example.
We would say as Orthodox Christians,
that the Holy Spirit works through the clergy and the lady
to make bread and wine be the body and blood of Christ on the altar in the liturgy.
But it's the Holy Spirit that does it.
Roman Catholicism teaches that the ordained priest and above
Right.
The Ornate priest has the power by saying the words of institution to consecrate the
Eucharist.
Yeah, which is, which is why it's indelible because you can't change back from being.
Even if he's deposed, he could still consecrate the Eucharist.
Yeah, now they would call it valid but illicit but still valid.
Like it still is the Eucharist.
He has the power to do it, right?
So that's sort of where the rubber meets the road example, right?
And this view interacts in interesting ways, right?
In the history of the West.
So a lot of people don't read St. Augustine's anti-donatist works, right?
Everybody likes to read the anti-plaging works and fight about it.
Uh...
Yeah.
Fewer still, I think, read the anti-manicain works.
But, so the Donatist argument gets misconstrued sometimes.
Yeah.
I think the way that most people...
Does it get short-handed?
Yeah.
The short-hand version is that people say that the Donatists were teaching that if someone,
if I clergy...
is a sinner, then his sacraments don't work, but they're not real. That basically his moral character
stops his sacramental ministry from actually working. Right. Right. And if you can, that would make sense.
right? Yeah.
the donatists held to like what's now the Eastern Orthodox view.
Right. If the donatists held to the idea that God was doing this through humans,
and they were just saying, well, hey, God wouldn't do that through an unworthy human.
Right. You could see the argument. They still be wrong, but you could see the argument.
Right. Yeah, but but that's actually not the argument they were actually making is more complicated.
a little bit more complicated. Yeah, it's it's really that
If you had been given the power to perform the sacraments, then you would be holy.
So grace that came, right?
The grace that came to you that would empower you to consecrate the Eucharist or to baptize
or to do these things, would have a transformative effect on you.
Yeah, and I mean, it's interesting.
actually an argument. Now I don't...
think it ever is official. But it is promulgated by a pope in the 11th century. The Dictactus Pope
I which says that the Pope becomes a saint by virtue of his office. Again, not an official Roman
Catholic teaching. But it's the same kind of idea, right? The idea that by virtue of being given
this particular grace, there is a transformative effect on the person such that they would not
in particular kinds of ways.
Right, and so, therefore...
If they sin in those ways, right, then that is proof that they don't have the grace to do what they're trying to do.
Yeah, which loops back then to that kind of shorthand version of the way people talk about the dentist.
Right, right. So the shorthand is completely wrong but it's lacking in nuance, right?
But that's evidence. And so of course the big issue that precipitated
Donatism was those who under tor-
or under threat denied Christ during the persecutions.
Right, they apostacized in the midst of that.
And then the question is, if they repent,
can they come back?
Can they?
Are they still clergy?
Yeah.
Yeah, and where are their sacraments
valid in the first place?
Ever, yeah, right.
There's a kind of retroactive.
Right, because clearly, they would have had the grace
to resist like the martyrs.
did right if they were holy people so this is evidence that they were sort of frauds all along
right and this is what you get when you believe in irresistible grace anyway so
right so St. Augustine is opposing the Donatists
And St. Augustine essentially agreed that Grace brought a kind of
power to do these things in terms of the sacraments. He was in line with the general Roman Catholic,
what later became the Roman Catholic view, the Western view. But he actually visited Donatists.
He visited Donatist churches, communities. And while there he saw genuine love
between people within those communities.
Right? You know, they were sort of rigorous. So this caused a problem for St. Augustine
because he held that view.
Caused a problem with his ecclesiology because he said, well, wait a minute.
Humans who aren't, haven't received the grace of God. Humans who haven't received this grace,
they can't love each other like this. Yeah. Right.
And so that must mean that the Daudetists, even though they're in schism,
still have something happening here.
Yeah. Right. And so the way, say to Gustard,
reconciled that is within the anti-Mannikian writings,
the anti-Daudetist writings, he still expresses a lively belief
with the freedom of the will. Right.
So, having a power doesn't mean you're useless.
that power. Having Dene Meece doesn't mean you actualize it, right? Yeah, so that's how he kind of
works it out. And that's and that's part of how he right he works it out. So I am now I feel like
I'm shitting deep and say this. I'm gonna sound briefly like I'm saying something nice about
out, John Calvin, and then I'm not. Um, well, that moment when our
Calvin.
friends actually become our Calvinist friends.
Do you mean there's a chance now?
So you're saying there's a chance.
So there is a quotation attributed to John Calvin.
And you said you've seen it attributed to Luther.
So it may just be a meme.
Who knows?
Yeah, it's kind of Reformation meme.
But the idea being that if the devil, this is talking about the whole
Donatist issue, right?
If the devil himself baptized you in the name of the Trinity, you'd be baptized.
Yes.
This is the most anti-dontantist thing that whoever that wrote said this could think of.
Yes, which may have been John Calvin or maybe not.
So the idea there being that who does it is irrelevant, right?
But now this also though, when you follow that out, and you can see this in Calvin's view,
of the sack.
and even more so in Calvin's successors view of the sacraments because frankly when you look at a lot of them
I don't think they understood what Calvin said about the Eucharist for example. I think they confused them and so they
went was wingly but
the and this is going to the sort of opposite pole where
The sacraments right and and God working is not mediated through a human at all
Yeah.
It's just me and Jesus.
Right.
So, while there's a certain sense where kind of all Christians could agree that Christ
is ultimately the minister of all sacraments, which is a sort of buzz phrase that comes
out of this.
Right.
A Roman Catholic could agree to that because they could say, well, the priest acts in persona
Christy.
So yeah.
And a Protestant could agree with that from coming from this kind of perspective.
I say, yeah, God just does it directly.
God acts, you know, the human is irrelevant.
Right.
but they're meaning very different things.
So in between this Western polarity of on the one hand,
the priest is invested with these powers to do these things,
which the he can then utilize it as will on the one hand.
And on the other hand, God just acts utterly independently of humans.
And does it need humans? Well, he doesn't need them,
does not stoop to use and work through here.
humans is the orthodox view that God acts through humans. So it is God acting, but it is
through humans. That has some consequences. That means that you being the person through
whom God acts in certain ways, meaning ordination or calling to any particular thing is revocable.
Yeah, right that a person.
and can be a priest and then not be a priest.
Right.
Because it's not a question of a power being given
and a power being taken away.
Right.
That power constituting a change of what something is again,
the playtinist thing out of here.
Yeah.
It's a continuity from God within the church.
Right.
I mean, the Holy Spirit dwelt in Saul.
Yeah.
And
powered him to be the king of Israel, right? God was working through him to establish justice,
right? And to exercise his reign over the people of Israel through Saul. And then he didn't.
Yeah, which left. Which it's interesting. So like, there's an interesting case that comes up then
of so leasization or deposition from the priesthood, right? Which is when someone,
And you know, when a man who's a priest or a deacon.
Or in some cases, a bishop has that removed from him by the authority over him.
Right?
Sometimes it's called defrocking.
And so they can no longer do the sacraments.
Now, in the Roman Catholic tradition, if that happens, then they're not allowed to do
the sacraments, but they can do the sacraments.
So that's why they have this category of
valid but illicit. So it's real, if a defrocked priest does the mass, the Eucharist is real,
but he's behaving illicitly, illegally, essentially within the church law. Whereas from the Orthodox
point of view, if someone's lay a size and he does not have the blessing, he's had his priest
to remove from him by his bishop, or if he's a bishop, his Episcopalcy removed by his synod,
then he can't...
to do those things. I mean, he could go through the motions, right? He could put on his
vestments and say the words and whatever, but it would not be. It would not be real. But then
what's interesting then in both traditions, there is the possibility for restoration, right?
So you could theoretically refrock, I guess, a defrock priest in the Roman Catholic Church for
the best of my knowledge. That's possibility. And they would say, well, he was validly a priest
the whole time.
time, but now his listlessness has been essentially returned to him. For the orthodox, the
possibility of restoration is there, and that's within the context of someone being
deposed unjustly. So there is within the canonical tradition the possibility for someone
being returned to the priesthood who was deposed unjustly. And when that's done, he's
not then reordained. Right? And so
one could say, oh well, you basically believe the same thing
the Catholics do.
And the answer to that is actually no.
That even though someone can be returned to the clerical
orders without an ordination, that they could not have performed
the Eucharist or other sacraments in a way that would be true
during that time when they were judged.
to be deposed, because the ministry is not something that is contained in the man.
It functions within the community of the church.
That's a pretty significant difference.
A laecized person cannot perform sacraments during that period of laecization, even if
it comes to an end at some point in the future, which is theoretically possible, although
it doesn't happen that often.
It is a thing people do get restored if the deposition was regarded.
is being unjust in some cases, probably not in every single case, but it has a thing that
has happened, for sure, in the past.
So this particular case sort of underlines that difference in the way that ordination
has understood between the Roman Catholic Church and the Orthodox Church.
Yeah.
And this also means that any given person for any given role, including various kinds
priesthood is interchangeable. Yeah. In the sense there is nothing about that person
that necessitates them being the one through whom God works. Yeah, there's not the young
sacraments and damn sacraments. It's a gift, right? So if I could no longer be a
service a priest, right? Another priest would come here.
Yep, right? Like, I am not...
like the only one, there's not some, it's a gift, there's not something about me, I didn't earn it,
I didn't achieve it, right? Like, it's a gift. Someone else could be the same gift God can do it
through anyone. If I just refuse, right? God will do it through someone else, right? Or just
directly, if we all refuse, right? He'll do what he'll do, right? And also, as you mentioned,
Right, this is priesthood is a role within the community.
Right.
This is the son.
role in task, it's a role in the community. So another difference between us and
Roman Catholic priesthood is that Orthodox priests cannot celebrate the Ugris by themselves.
Yeah, there is no solo divine liturgy. It's not a thing. Right. And so that is because we have to
have the community there. We have to have the lady there because we're serving that role
in and for.
the community it's not just an ability that we have. Indeed. All right we're
gonna take our second and final break and in the third half we'll be back and
we will finally actually talk about the actual right of ordination itself. So
this is our want. As is our what all right. We'll take a break later. Exactly and
we'll be right back. Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of
of spirits. Give them a call at 8
855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
A collection of short stories available now
on the Ancient Faith Bookstore.
Sometimes poignant, sometimes funny, sometimes heartbreaking,
sometimes convicting.
These stories of life in an inner city immigrant Orthodox
or guarantee
to shake your assumptions and make you see your life and face in a new way.
They are not for the faint of heart, but they are very much for all who want to embrace the truth more fully.
And you didn't have to ask Rusk over for help, cleaning, polishing, carrying, in or out.
Any work in the church, the woman was a stalled, a tallotage you could count on.
No one knew her suffering.
They never bothered to...
look into our eyes. It surprised me that most of the church folks at St. Alexander the
world-ing-durch parish didn't even know her name. It wasn't anything they'd thought
about.
To find this book and others like it, you can go to store.enginefaith.com. Again, that
is store.enginefaith.com
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Steven DeYoung. If you have a question...
Call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back.
It's the third half of Lord Spirit's Podcast.
And we're continuing to talk about ordination.
This is the fourth in our series
on the Sacraments of the Orthodox Church.
And this is our final episode before the end of this year.
Can you believe it?
Yes, I have a calendar.
Yeah.
Father Stevens level of incredulity is never at the same height as mine, apparently.
True.
I face hard facts.
Yeah.
It's true.
We'll be back in the new year.
Second Thursday of January, of course, although that's going to be a pre-recorded episode.
Yeah.
The UNI are both going to be in, we're going to be convening in a special way.
Right? Deep in the heart of Texas.
I guess. I'm not sure where Dallas isn't Texas actually, because I'm not looking at a map of Texas.
Technical, I don't know if Dallas is technically North Texas.
If it's not, it's right on the edge.
You go up to Denton, you're definitely in North Texas.
So I think Dallas kind of counts as North Texas.
Okay. Well, I mean, I'm just hearing the yellow rows of Texas in my head right now, but it's okay.
You know that song?
actually, but no, I don't care about that on air. Okay. No. So you'll look it up later. Yeah.
I used to know. I don't want to know anymore now. Right. We're talking about ordination. We're not
talking about Texas. Yeah. Let's be down. But in Dallas, I'm going to do a commercial.
When in Dallas, go by Titan Comics and say hi to Jeremy Shore, the owner and proprietor
or scomic store in what is problem
North Texas we just kind of established. Anyway, I'm just doing all these free commercials now.
I know, right? I'm gonna have to come up with one like every episode just potentially completely
at random just for somebody I like somewhere with a business right? I know. I should throw some
commercials on my own. I'm just putting that out there as well. Saturday, Saturday, Saturday.
Yeah. So the actual right of ordination, yes, now we're actually going to talk about the
true nation of Aaron and his sons, two hours and 35 minutes into this episode. Yes.
We get to do it. People. That's how we do it. You're not only the groundwork. Okay. So
to the second most popular, at least popular book of the Torah, in that that Torah tier.
the tierings. Yeah right right. Lovetticus. Everybody loves Lovetticus.
It's got a lot of narrative in it actually by the way, everybody.
It really does.
Yeah, it really does.
Once you get to the holiness code, less so, mostly commandments.
Right.
But you got to pay attention to that stuff.
Less the earth swallow you up or that kind of thing.
That is very important stuff.
Right.
Yeah.
That people should spend more time with.
But anyway, there's a commercial for the book of Leviticus.
Have you considered the book of Leviticus?
Turn to chapter 8.
Read the Sintillating Story of Aaron's
Ordination in His Sons.
This is a great story.
Yeah, yeah.
We're going to go through it on my line, right?
Yes, mostly unread.
Yeah.
Byf, right?
All right, so we begin.
The slow walk through Leviticus 8.
Let's begin now.
Okay, verse 1.
The Lord spoke to Moses saying,
take Aaron and his sons with him
and the garments and the anointing oil.
and the bull of the sin offering and the two rams and the basket of unleavened bread
and assemble all the congregation at the entrance of the tent of meeting and
Moses did as the Lord commanded him and the congregation was assembled at the
entrance of the tent of meeting. What I like about the first four verses is
that if you've ever read a service text like the one that comes from the
Eddie O'Kid archdiocese there's always this little light sometimes it's a
smaller print at the beginning that's aimed at us priests that is just like this
like
Here's all the stuff you need.
Set a table here and put this on it.
The bits in the tilex or the red, you know?
Yeah.
The printed, this is the setup, right?
For the ordination ritual that's about to take place.
And the reason for that is,
this isn't just a historical recounting of,
oh, isn't this interesting?
How Aaron way back then was ordained.
It's, this is also setting out the practice
for future high-prests.
I do it in the future. Yeah. Yeah. Yep. Yep. Okay. Verse five, and Moses said to the congregation,
this is the thing that the Lord has commanded to be done. Sorry, saying, look, I didn't make this
up myself. Right. This is God said. Now is the time for the Lord to have. Oh, yeah.
Verse six. The most, Moses brought Aaron and his sons and washed them with water.
And he put the code on him and tied the sash around
his waist and clothed him with the robe and put the ephod on him, and tied the skillfully
woven band of the ephod around him, binding it to him with the band. And he placed the
breast piece on him, and in the breast piece he put the urim and the thumem, and he set
the turban on his head, and on the turban in front, he set the golden plate, the holy crown,
as the Lord commanded Moses.
So a couple things to notice here.
Right.
First, right, that part of this is him being vested. Yeah. Right. By someone else. By Moses. Right. Yep.
Moses, Vesem. Moses is essentially the efficient of this ordination. Even though not ordained himself. Not a priest himself. Not ordained to this priesthood himself. Yeah.
But this is God said somebody's going to do the first one. You got to do it, right?
Aaron can do the next one, but somebody's gonna do
the first one. I mean, if you pick somebody to do the first one, Moses seems like a good choice.
Yeah. Um, so and for Orthodox folks, if you've ever been doing an Orthodox ordination,
right? The person is vested, right? Yeah, by the by the bishop and those assisting him.
Right, by the efficient of the of the ordination and orthodox folks, you may know that the
Bishop is vested every time he comes to serve.
But also, notice the pattern of the procedure here, right?
He's washed in his sons, right?
They're washed with water and then they're vested.
You may already see a pattern emerging.
Yes, a baptism of sorts.
Yes, in the I mean, the literally baptism service
us, right? Washed, vested. This is going to continue, right? But this is, this is what
I was hinting at, right? With, uh, with our collar. Yeah, right. A kind of a kind of
ordination, right? A kind of ordination to a kind of priesthood, right? Yeah. Um, and
if you think of Israel as a whole, they're baptized in Nemozes. Yep. Through the Red Sea.
Right yeah, so first
10.
Okay, verse 10.
Then Moses took the anointing oil, and anointed the tabernacle, and all that was in it,
and consecrated them.
And he sprinkled some of it on the altar seven times, and anointed the altar in all
its utensils and the basin and its stand to consecrate them.
And he poured some of the anointing oil on Aaron's head, and anointed him to consecrate
him.
And Moses brought Aaron's sons and clothed them with coats and tied sashes around their
were weasts and bound caps on them as
the Lord commanded Moses. So there's this anointing, right? I mean, this is just like so far in some
ways, this is just like an Orthodox baptism service. They get chrismated. Yeah, the Washington
and then the clothing and then the chrysmation. Right. And this is also the, we're going to see this
pattern play out as we move out through the chapter where something is done to the altar
and then to Aaron and the sons.
Right.
So, the altar is anointed.
The altar is chrismated.
We talked about this a little bit last time.
The chrismation of the elements of the tabernacle, right?
And then Aaron is also connecting Aaron to the altar and the accretra mall of the tabernacle,
right?
So that Aaron effectively is being made part of the tabernacle.
He's being linked to it.
Yeah.
Yeah and it's and
It's worth pointing out like the things that are the physical stuff, the kind of the
holy hardware.
They're not turned into a different kind of thing than the things that they're like on
the outside, right?
You know utensils.
So utensils are utensils, but these utensils are set aside for use in the tabernacle, but
there's still utensils.
There's still meat out of whatever they're made out of.
Just as Aaron does not become
a different kind of species or whatever by being ordained. He's still a man, but he's
set aside now for this task. This is...
And dedicated to this purpose. Yeah. So the chalice is not different from my Star Trek
Rath of Conan collector cup because it's made from metal, mined out of the Holy Mountain.
Right. Right. It's the purpose for which it has been set aside.
Yeah, it's the function. It's the way that it's being treated.
right. Yeah it was about innate holiness. I mean.
Come on, Rathacan.
I don't know.
I mean, there's stuff I like about Rathacan for sure, but the...
It's virtually a relic of Shatner.
The earworm thing...
Great moment, instead of a...
Ratch itself around your cerebral cortex.
Very creepy.
Making you suggestible.
Super creepy.
Okay, verse 14.
he brought the bowl of the sin offering and Aaron and his sons lead their
hands on the head of the bull of the sin offering. So what's going on? Are they putting the sins
of the people on the... Don't get excited. Oh. With the atonement theories. Oh, sorry.
We'll leave off the atonement theories. They do not say anything. Yeah. Yeah. It's a sin offering,
but it doesn't have any sins on it.
Right. They just put their hands on it.
Yeah. Right.
to say this one. Right. They're
designated this bull for this
purpose. Right. Designating again.
Lots of bulls. This one is going to
be the sin offering. Yeah. Yeah. Right.
And that'll become even more clear
here as we move move on to the next
bit. Okay. Verse 15. Andy killed it.
No big fancy ritual. Yeah. So we don't
know well. We don't know how. We don't
don't know where we don't know where.
What?
Just, the bull is now dead.
But you have to kill it in order to.
And Moses took the blood.
Yes.
And with his finger, put it on the horns of the altar
around it and purified the altar
and poured out the blood at the base of the altar
and consecrated it to make a tonement for it.
The altar.
Yes, for the altar.
He's making the altar for the altar.
Right?
Because the altar did bad things.
No way.
There's no sins that the altar committed. Yeah, no that are being put on the bowl
It's the bowls being killed instead. That doesn't make sense
Right. Yeah, it's to clean up the altar from the sins accumulated of the people right is part of setting it aside to be the altar of
God that it must be purified yeah, as we said before previous episode's life stuff kills death stuff
There you go, right? It's a blood is life stuff
takes care smears away wipes away absorbs
want to see it, or argue about it in your journal article, right? But it takes care of it.
All right, verse 16, and he took all the fat that was on the entrails and the long lobe of the liver.
I love eliteration. And the two kidneys with their fat and Moses burned them on the altar.
But the bull and its skin and its flesh and its dung, he burned up with fire outside the camp
as Lord commanded Moses.
Right. So an important element of this for what we were saying before about not putting
sins on it, right, is that notice there are clean parts of the bowl and unclean parts
of the bowl, right? The the dung, right, the excrement being obviously unclean, right?
The unclean parts of the bowl cannot be put on the altar. Yeah, you don't give God that
garbage right that gets taken outside.
the camp and burned. Right? So I've been kept in the camp. Right? It is the good parts.
Right? So if you put sins on the bull, the bull is now unclean and impure. And I sin on it,
you can't put any of it on the altar. Yeah, because remember when you're offering something to God,
you don't give him some dirty sinful thing. Right? You give him what's good and pure.
without blemish. Yeah. Yeah.
Right. Alright, verse 18, that he presented the ram of the burnt offering, and Aaron and his sons
laid their hands on the head of the ram. This is not a sin offering. Yeah, again. But there's still
the laying out of hands and there's two ram's there. This one's being designated for the burnt offering.
Right. And he killed it and Moses threw the blood against the sides of the altar.
He cut the ram and...
to pieces and Moses burned the head and the pieces and the fat. He washed the entrails
and the legs with water and Moses burned the whole ram on the altar. It was a burnt
offering with a pleasing aroma, a food offering for the Lord as the Lord commanded Moses.
Right. So this is a whole burnt offering. Yeah. I mean, God gets all of it. God gets
the whole thing. The whole thing is going to get burned up. But look at what Moses has
to do in the process.
In order to offer the whole thing, he has to wash and clean the unclean parts.
Yeah, before he can, right?
I'll be purified.
Again, you don't give God something with sin in it.
Which is the opposite.
Right?
Yes.
Yeah.
Okay.
Continuing on, verse 22, then he presented the other ram, the ram of ordination.
Aaron and his sons laid their hands
on the head of the ram. And he killed it, and Moses took some of its blood, and put it on the
lobe of Aaron's right ear, and on the thumb of his right hand, and on the big toe of his right foot.
Then he presented Aaron's sons, and Moses put some of the blood on the lobes of their right ears,
and on the thumbs of their right hands, and on the big toes of their right feet, and Moses through
through the blood against the sides of the altar.
So this is kind of weird.
Really? You've never had that done?
No. No.
Just not a joint and skull and bones at you.
Anyway. Yeah.
Yeah, weirdly, I didn't go to Yale.
I don't know.
So, um, the, so we have, right, the base level, we have this same sort of motif again of
something being put on the altar and on Aaron and his sons, right, connecting them.
Right. Right. Right.
And the particularity here with the blood, right?
Well, first of all, it should be noted that this is unusual.
Yeah, usually you don't put blood on people
in the rituals of the Old Testament.
Blood is not put on people.
Blood is put on things, normally, right?
Blood on the day of atonement,
the blood is used to purify things, not people.
The places, there's a few places,
a handful of places where blood gets put on people.
In the Torah, one of them is when the covenant...
is ratified. Yeah.
How cyanide, they get sprinkled with blood.
Right? Remember what I said to the caller?
Here in the word as usual.
And one is here.
And so here in particular, the blood that's going to be the
altars put on the right earlobe, the right thumb and the and
the right big toe.
So the earlobe is...
The earlobe was pierced with an all to mark a slave, right?
Yeah.
When that slave was being made
a sort of a permanent member of the household.
Yeah, so this is a kind of ritual wounding sort of,
but they're not actually piercing Aaron's ear,
but it's a ritual piercing, sort of speak,
but not an act of piercing.
So he's being made a servant of that altar
And...
He is being brought into the household of God.
Yeah.
Right.
Economy of God, right?
There in the Tabernacle, right?
Which is another piece of this kind of angelic role.
Right.
And then so that's the earlobe, the right thumb, right?
The right hand is the dexra one.
And so that represents the things you do, right, your hands and your feet are where you
go, right?
You're right, big toe, right?
Is so it's what you do where you go.
He's a servant, right?
And he's part of the household of God.
Okay.
That is sons.
All right.
This is the part where you get to the bacon buns
telling everybody now. Verse 25,
Then he took the fat and the fat tale and all the fat that was on the entrails and
the long lobe of the liver and the two kidneys with their fat and the right thigh
and out of the basket of unleavened bread that was before the Lord, he took one
unleavened loaf and one loaf of bread with oil and one wafer and placed them on
the pieces of fat and on the right thigh. And he put all these in the hands of
Aaron and in the hands of his sons and waived
them as a wave offering before the Lord. Then Moses took them from their hands and burned
them on the altar with the burnt offering. This was an ordination offering with the pleasing
aroma, a food offering to the Lord. And Moses took the breast and waved it for a wave offering
before the Lord. It was Moses' portion of the ram of ordination as the Lord commanded
Moses. So what's the deal with wave offerings?
Right. So they're throwing their lunch.
in the air and waving like they just don't care.
Right.
But they do care.
Thank you.
In a normal wave offering, and Moses, the Moses bit in verse 29, there is the normal kind
of wave offering, right?
Is that the priest's portion of an offering, as we said before, we talked about sacrifice.
the sacrifices offer there's a portion of it that goes to the priests.
Right. And the priest portion, nonetheless, before the priest took it to eat it, it was offered
as a wave offering. Yeah, it was a give it to God and then go and eat it and receive it back.
Right. Yeah. Right. God's the idea that even this that is my portion really belongs to God and God
is giving it to me right to feed me.
Yeah right.
And so with Moses, this is sort of the normal procedure in this particular of the ordination right,
the portion that would have been normally Aaron's and his sons gets burnt and offered to God.
And I think that some Moses gets to eat some because he's not being ordained.
Right. He is the one to work. Yeah, but the ones who are being ordained,
and their portion of
essentially gets given to God and burned.
Right. So if Aaron ordains his grandson, he would get the
brass.
As the efficient right.
Yeah. Yeah.
Okay.
Verse 30.
Then Moses took some of the anointing oil and of the blood
that was on the altar and sprinkled it on Aaron and his
garments and also on his sons and his sons garments.
So he consecrated Aaron and his car.
and his sons and his sons garments with him.
So there's another connection with the altar, right?
The blood from the altar and the oil.
Blood and oil now, right, mixed together.
Right.
And we have the sprinkling like the covenant.
Yeah.
So for the perspective of the preceding portions of the Torah,
Israel's history, right, of passing through the sea
and the cloud and the being sprinkled with blood
that pedicoster sign.
and it's sort of being recapitulated in the ordination ritual.
Right?
Because again, the high priest is the representation of Israel.
Yeah.
Right?
Sort of Israel summed up in one person, including in the case of Christ.
Most fully in the case of Christ.
And then from our perspective, we're looking back at our baptismal ritual,
also based on the same thing.
those connections there, right? Yeah, and I mean, I think it's worth pointing out, like, now there's
what I didn't count, but like four or five ways that a thing is done to the altar and done to
Aaron's sons. So there's this deep, deep connection between them and this altar. And you know, this
persists even into the priesthood of the church, where people
are ordained, men are ordained for particular altars. And actually it's my understanding
that the earliest ordination rights, especially for bishops in particular, I think this is
still the case with bishops. But even with priests and deacons, part of the ordination
right was actually to say which altar, I mean it's usually the one that they're at, that
the man is being ordained for, right, they could for this altar in particular. And early
early on.
There
weren't transfers of clergy at all. You were ordained for one alter and that's the one
you serve for your life. Later on, you know, the idea of transferring clergy, but they're
still transferred, like they're taken from one alter and then they're attached to another
alter. So they only attach to one alter. And there's no such thing as priests or deacons
or even bishops at large roaming free. Yeah. I mean, there is a, there's a lovely Latin
there are
some, but there shouldn't be. There's a lovely, lovely Latin term for this, which is a
Piscopi Vagantus, wandering bishops. But yeah, it's not a thing in the Orthodox church where
a priest does not exist without an alter, he does not exist without a bishop. That's not a thing.
It's not because again, we don't believe that the priesthood is a kind of power that a man holds
on his own.
Right. His connection to the altar is a significant piece of the way that we understand priesthood
to work in ordination to work as functioning within a community and for the community and
by the community.
You know, there's no at large clergy.
It's just not a thing.
There are large clergy.
There are large clergy, but not at large.
I mean, you and not small, my friend.
I am not.
Compared to most other humans.
Right? I'm slightly smaller, but not a huge amount. I wish I'm more smaller, but I'm not.
So okay, verse 31, and Moses said to Aaron and his sons, boil the flesh at the entrance
of the tent of meeting, and they're eat it and the bread that is in the basket of ordination
offerings as I commanded, saying, Aaron and his sons, shall eat it. And what remains the
flash and the bread you shall burn up with fire.
And you shall not go outside the entrance of the tent of meeting for seven days, until
the days of your ordination are completed, Fred will take seven days to ordain you.
As has been done today, the Lord has commanded to be done to make atonement for you.
At the entrance of the tent of meeting you shall remain day and night for seven days, performing
with the Lord has charged so that you do not die.
For I have for so I have been commanded.
And Aaron and his sons did all the things that the Lord commanded by.
Moses, seven-day ordination.
Weeklong. That's a long ordination, sir.
Yes. But yeah, and so they stay, they live there. And that, you know, verse 34,
right, to make a tonement for you, we have to understand in the same sense as making a tonement
for the altar. Yeah, they're being purified. They're being purified, and they're being sort of
fully removed from the world.
And...
attached to the tabernacle in the way the various objects, right?
And other things in the tabernacle are.
Yeah.
Right.
And so, seven, right, it's the number of fullness and completion at all, because of the
seven planets, see previous episodes.
There you go.
Jewish astrology, everybody.
So, um, right.
So we, we commented on our way through, right?
some of the continuities with later ordination, right?
We see already in the pages of the New Testament,
this setting apart of people by the laying out of hands
by an efficient.
So, and this is connected to that laying out of hands
as we talked about last time in the Christmas episode,
was sort of the original means we see in the New Testament.
of conveying the Holy Spirit, right? And we see the the hands we laid in Aaron and
his son's ordination on the animals to designate them for this particular purpose.
Yep, right. And so this both of those are tied together. This idea of God acting
through people in the case of the interwelling of the whole...
spirit. God is going to act through them in this particular way and they are designated for that
through the laying on of hands. Yeah. Right. So some summary kind of comments
That's right.
So clergy are expected to be separate in the sense of holiness as we discuss.
but in our contemporary world, what that actually means can sometimes be ambiguous.
Yeah, because people take the word holiness to mean being super good.
Or separation. Yeah. Yeah.
So sometimes people think that means being weird, especially people in seminaries.
It's a really full of weirdos, especially when I was in one.
That's true.
That's the...
B
normal. Yeah. That's um and the kind of holiness that clergy should at least aspire to is not
making a pretence of piety. Yeah. Looking big and priestlyish. Right. From from first head experience,
you're sometimes given that impression in seminary. That it's about appearing priestly
went in public talking in.
walking in a priestly way. And number one, that reads is pretty phony, just about everyone,
eventually. And also, if you want something that is criticized continually by the Lord throughout
the gospels, it's publicly acting pious. Yeah. They have their reward. Say they're long.
prayers, where the veggies were all right, going and making a public show of your piety,
nothing positive is said about that anywhere in the scriptures, but especially not the
gospels. So that is definitely not what any clergy person is called to. Yeah. Yeah. I mean,
so like what is it about? It's number one, it's that the clergy are held to a higher standard,
not in the sense that there's
different standards, but rather in the sense largely that the enforcementist stricter.
Right. The same rules. Yeah. Yeah. There's not things that are
sins for the lay lady and not sins for the clergy or that are sins for the clergy and not for the
similarity, sin and sin, right?
But clergy are, you know, like the, the penalty is,
is stricter. So like there's a number of canonical crimes as it were, that it says if a layman
does this, let him be excommunicated, but if a clergyman let him be deposed. And in order
to understand why what the clergyman is getting in that case is more severe than the layman,
You need to know that excommunication is temporary and the purpose of it is.
to bring so much repentance, and then they can be returned to communion, whereas deposition
unless it's unjust, but deposition is permanent. Your vocation is over. That's it. It's over.
Right. The church will go on. God will continue to do what he does, but he'll be doing certain
elements of it through someone else. Yeah. Right. Right. Yeah. And sort of the exhibit
of that is probably divorce.
Right.
It's always a sin.
in.
It's always a sin because you're always doing harm to yourself and to other people
Yep, and it's the product of sin right if
People weren't sinners. They wouldn't get divorced right
The marriages that last also contain two sinners right but that's
So it's always a sin. It's always an issue. It's always a problem
It's always something that requires healing and forgiveness and restoration right but
if you're
clergy and
you get divorced, right?
That is treated more seriously and you're gonna be deposed.
Yeah, I mean, there are sometimes,
I've known of exceptions that are made,
but the standard thing is deposition.
Yes, those are exceptions for a reason.
They're exceptional instances.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, so I mean, there's a number of things
that clergy can do that get them leasized, right?
Things that they would just be leasized for.
We're not gonna look at them.
Because you did that, now you can no longer
Thank you.
this, right? Think of King David not being allowed to build the temple.
Right. Right. And I mean, I think it's worth pointing out that it doesn't mean that clergy
who commit those sins cannot be forgiven. They can be forgiven, but forgiveness does not
mean restoration to your priesthood. You know, you can become a saint. You can even become
saint but that's not the same thing as as
you know, serving as clergy, right?
King David is a saint.
Yeah.
He was forgiven of his sins when he repented.
Yeah, he was not more like, you know, the one to build the temple.
Moses, I mean, Moses, right?
Moses has his priesthood removed and he's clearly a saint.
Yes.
You know, and he has a remove because of something bad that he did.
You know, you know, yes, yes.
There are consequences.
Right.
Yeah.
were these things and and repentance
is not the stuff you have to do to not face the consequences.
Right.
Part of repentance is facing the consequences.
Yeah, of your actions.
Not getting, not a way to get out of them.
Yes.
And so as a final note,
because we want to end on a very non-controversial note.
I knew you were gonna say exactly that.
Yes.
When the issue of women's ordination comes up, right, it is important.
This is a place where it's especially important
that we focus on the kind of orthodox view that we've outlined here, right?
Because in a lot of Protestant circles, the discussion surrounds women's ability.
Yeah, can they do the things that a priest does?
She could actually preach really well or she
She's a really good Bible teacher or she's a really good counselor or she's a the things
that a certain ordained office does.
This person is good at right.
So why shouldn't they do it right because the things they're good at are gifts given
to them by God right.
So it's key to remember as nothing to do with any ability anybody has.
Yeah right.
one who can read, conserve the divine energy.
Right and if you didn't know how to read you could memorize it right
Right, so it's not a question of ability
Right who has who has the ability? It's not something achieved. It's not something right yeah
I mean, you know even as even as it is it's not like
There's a singing contest
You know and if you wouldn't be increased if you win the singing I wasn't gonna say anything but
But you know, only the
who win the singing contest get to be ordained like that's not I am the William Hung of Orthodox
Priests. So the uh well father had to collect himself. So the the issue of women's ordination again
in in Roman Catholic circles and some Protestant circles because again you can't generalize about
Protestantism, it's not just one thing.
It's an issue of authority and power.
Right.
The church is investing authority and power in males and not females.
And so, again, if you're understanding, right, is not that, that it is not based on some
granted authority or power, right.
then it becomes about God has called particular people to do particular things.
Right. And different people are different. This is St. Paul with the spiritual gifts.
Right. God is called different people to do different things. And he has called men to not just men in general, but specific men.
Right. To do specific things and specific women to do specific things. Right.
And...
there are areas where those don't overlap.
Yeah, I mean, one of them is being a spiritual father
or a spiritual mother.
Those two things require you to be one or the other sex.
Yeah, I can't be a spiritual mother.
And a spiritual mother is not simply
the same as a spiritual father but female.
There are two different things.
Yes.
Yeah.
Now I'll really get canceled.
A biological male can't give birth.
Well, I mean, you say that and we're going to just renew your contract actually.
No, okay.
Yeah.
I didn't say cancel by you.
There is no contract yet.
Yeah, that's right.
Yeah.
This is at will.
No.
And I mean, it's also worth pointing out.
I mean, this might be an uncomfortable thing to say, but it's actually worth pointing out
that God never ordained any women.
Like you don't see in Scripture that ever happening.
He could have given the priesthood to Miriam instead of Aaron.
Right. He totally could have. He could have he could have ordained his mother. Christ could have ordained his mother
You know, but it's not because these women are
lesser than men or anything like that. That's not what it's about
God did
So pretty amazing things through the Theotokos like yeah kind of a nation that we celebrate in a couple days better than everybody else
Yeah, right
Yeah, she's the one human through whom God did that work, right took flesh, right? So
You know, compared to doing the liturgy, kind of wins, but, right?
Celebrate liturgy is a very high honor, right?
I'm not demeaning that, but I'm saying women, particularly, again, it's particular women, and particular men.
particular women have been called to far greater works of God through faithfulness
than particular men have.
Yeah. Well, let's wrap up. You know, I remembered very clearly when we talked about, for
instance earlier, the Pada Kata Thiki, the pledge, you know, where the Bishop places the
body of Christ into the hands of the newly ordained priest. When I was ordained, which now
is a little over 16 years ago.
to the priesthood.
Someone, it was really very nice.
Someone took an actual photo of that moment.
And so I have a photo of Bishop Antoon.
God rest his soul,
putting the body of Christ into my hands.
And I look at that photo a lot,
and I will often reread the prayer,
the words that he's said.
And I remember Bishop Antoon,
he had a particular way of saying that a bit about where,
you know, you're gonna be.
call to an account, I think Bishop Antoon would say it, he's going to ask you about it. Right?
And you know, from a personal point of view, I remember being scared out of my mind at that moment.
I don't think I was shaking or whatever, but I just remember hearing Bishop Antoon say that and
thinking and looking down there at this consecrated
body of Christ and just trying to imagine what all of that means. And I recall also the first time
that I celebrated the divine liturgy which for me actually it just so happened that it was on
the feast of Saint Raphael of Brooklyn. That was the very first time that I celebrated the liturgy
as the celebrant. Obviously I celebrated it, I con- celebrated it with Bishop Antoon for the rest
the day that you're dating me, you know, but the first time that I actually...
I celebrated myself was on the Feast of St. Rafael Brooklyn.
And I remember thinking a number of times in the course of that event,
those events, like feeling like a fake, what do they call that?
Imposter syndrome, right?
I have to imagine that a lot of clergy probably feel that, especially initially.
And I will say, you know, in that the, you know, more than a decade and a half since then,
have not felt any zapp.
come out of my hands as I serve the liturgy or any, you know, magical energy or whatever.
But I remember having the feeling of like, I can't believe that I'm standing here and doing this.
I can't believe they let me do this. And I try to remember that not so I can just sort of go
through a psychological journey again. But rather, precisely for the point, one of these points
that we've been making is that it's
c-
God who does this?
It's not me.
I mean, when a priest commutes himself,
or even when he's being commuted by the bishop,
he refers to himself as the most unworthy presbyter.
Right?
I'm not worthy.
The fact that I was ordained did not turn me
into a worthy thing.
I'm still the most unworthy.
And I say that not to sort of
display my humility, whatever, it's just an actual fact that none of us are made worthy
in the sense of becoming, you know, super Christians or saints or whatever.
We are simply set aside to do a particular task.
And I revisit those thoughts and I look at those photos and I think about the things that
Bishop Untoon said precisely to remind myself that this does not belong to me.
It is Christ's priesthood and he functions through those who are
deemed to do this work.
Now I imagine most of the people listening to this are not ordained clergy and
never will be.
Those who are ordained were not necessarily special.
I'm definitely not.
I have known some very holy priests in my day but I'm not one of them.
.
If you're listening to this and you think, okay, I just listened to them talk about ordination for the last three hours and 17 minutes.
What does that have to do with me?
I think one of the big takeaways is that God is always working and He can work and is working through you.
And so the question always is, is in what way do I need to cooperate with what God is doing right now?
And it's using not a big mystery. It's the good thing you have in front of you to do.
That's the thing you should be doing
Right. So as you know, as Father Stephen mentioned, while we're not ordained, all ordained as
deacons, presbyters and bishops, we all are in a sense ordained into a kind of priesthood.
I mean, we saw in the priest in the ordination of Aaron and his sons, basically the basic
elements of a baptismal service, right? The washing, the clothing.
the Christmas, all Orthodox Christians receive all that. That's all part of who we are.
And we're all brought into the order of the laity. And that's not something that clergy
leave behind, right? The most basic garment that we wear, the stichadion, is the baptismal
garment. That's what that is. And it shows that we are brought into the communion of the
the church to function.
as the church to be the church. And of course, as we've talked about many times in this podcast,
what is the church? It's the body of Christ. We are Christ's powers, his actions in this world
in as much as we cooperate with the Holy Spirit. And that is awesome. That is awesome. And
ordained ministry in the clergy is part of that. It's not apart from that. It's not
a radically different thing than that. It's simply a part of that. It's a particular role within that.
And it's meaningless without it.
Clergy don't function without the church. Again, that's why we don't have priests at large.
We don't have bishops at large. We don't have deacons at large. None of us are at large.
With every single canonical Orthodox clergyman, he can point you, this is my altar, this is my bishop.
This is the synod that this bishop belongs to.
like these are not big mysteries.
And that's because it's God working through us, not God handing a special power over to us.
And that's one of the most important concepts I think from this episode. Father?
So, Saint Paul, famously, I guess, everything you said of the Bible because it's in the Bible
all the framers again.
said that not many of you should presume to be teachers.
And he had to say that because many people were presuming to be teachers.
And that has continued down to the present day, I think, undeniably.
We as humans have a tendency to follow our desire.
to follow the things that we at least think that we want.
The things that we think will fill something that's lacking in us
or give us some, be instrumental to give us something that we want,
whether that's power or control or freedom.
We see people and choices we make as instruments to gain those things
game those things.
that we think we want, that we think we'll make us happy and feel fulfilled. And one of those things
within the community of the church is ordained office. And that's envisaged in different ways by
different people that some people view it either because it's the teaching of
their church or just the way the community functions, or even if it's against the way
the community is supposed to function, they view this as a position of power. They view
this as a position of authority. This is a position. Sometimes in some communities you have
an impoverished community with a local pastor who at least presents the image of being
quite well off and having quite the lifestyle.
So this could be money, this could be a way out of poverty.
There are all kinds of things that this can seem to entail.
Maybe someone is deeply struggling with sin and thinks that devoting themselves more fully
to the life of the church is going to be the thing that helps break them out of that
and give them victory over that, just sort of de facto as a sort of trade.
world. I did it to keep my life to God.
he'll deliver me from this.
And then if God forbid those folks do receive ordained office,
they find that that struggle just gets worse
and real disasters happen.
But all of these things are the sort of pursuit of desire.
And the first place none of them are what the priesthood is
actually about.
I've never met anyone who is
said, I want to be ordained as a priest because I want to shoulder the burden of the sins of my community.
Because I want to go home at night and have trouble sleeping because I'm worried about what's
going on in this person's marriage or with their kids. Or someone who I deeply respected and looked
up to came to me in confession today.
and told me something that I don't even know how to process that they did it let
alone what I should tell them to do to try to help them. Nobody seems to
desire that. Nobody seems to desire the reality that I as a priest let alone
what a bishop will face at the last judgment.
When we stand before Christ and have to give an answer not only for ourselves, but for
everyone we served and how we interacted with them and how we helped or failed to help
or advise or failed to advise those other people.
People don't want that responsibility part.
That's what St. Paul was talking about when he said not many of you should presume to be
teachers because of the judgment. It's expressly what he said.
But more importantly, as much as it's been bred into us, sort of post-froid, that we
should all follow our desires or follow our bliss, right?
This we go out seeking that thing that will make us happy, that will fill in our lack,
it will, you know, finally make us complete and perfect us.
That doesn't work.
It never works.
When you get the thing you desire,
it doesn't make you complete.
It doesn't fill the lack.
And so one of two things happens.
You move on to the next thing.
The next most more powerful position.
The next level of influence.
The next amount of wealth.
The next promotion.
the next trophy spout.
the next whatever. And eventually, after that's happened a few times, it's different for
different people, that's when you get truly blackpilled. That's when you realize, you know
what, nothing is going to make me happy. Nothing is going to fix this. Nothing is going to make
me feel complete. This quest is endless and will never be satisfied. Right? And that could
It can be very dark.
place to end up if the only way of living life you've ever known is pursuing the things
you desire. The flip side of that has to do with the Holy Spirit and the way we've talked
about spirits in general and the Holy Spirit in particular in the last several episodes
of the
podcast. And that's that the Holy Spirit himself, God has agency, right? God is
it work in the world and can be at work through us. And so rather than trying to
figure out what it is we want, sometimes we don't even know. Rather than
trying to figure out what it is we want, what it is that might make us happy,
becoming more sensitive to the Holy Spirit feels a little bit more like doing what we feel compelled to do.
Doing what we know is right.
Doing what we know should be done.
And in most cases, we do actually know that because it is true, as we talked about last time,
that the Holy Spirit has written the commandments upon our heart.
We know when we see someone's
struggling we should help. We know when we see someone being belittled we should
intervene. We know what we need to do about suffering about the impoverished
person who's asking us for help. We know what we should do. But because we've
become insensitive to the Holy Spirit we don't feel compelled to actually do
What?
We don't.
feel the push, right? We don't feel the drive. And that is what first and foremost
fostering that sensitivity is about. We do that in prayer. We do that by doing hard
things, forcing ourselves, even when we don't feel like it, even when we don't feel compelled.
But ultimately, the best advice I got in terms of how I ended up being a priest was
from actually a Roman Catholic priest who was the, who had the same last name as me, no
relation. Who told me that before you become a priest, before you become clergy, you should
try to do everything else. You should try and work any other job that you think you might
enjoy that might work for you.
you, you should go and get a nice car, you should write. And it is Roman Catholic context,
he said he told me that he tells people who want to be Roman Catholic priests, they should
go out and date, do all those things. Right. Because if God wants you to be a priest,
if that's the particular role, he's calling you to, if that's the work he wants to go
through you, you won't be able to do anything else.
Ultimately, you'll be compelled to do it.
You'll be driven to do it.
And you'll find yourself doing things like shouldering burns and responsibilities and
sins of the people that you never would have said you wanted to or desired to.
But you'll do it because it's the only thing you can do.
This isn't isolated to the priesthood because as we said, there's lots of different kinds
of priesthood.
There's a certain priesthood that's practiced by parents and a family. There's a certain priesthood that's that's practiced as
a leader in various other community areas even within the church. There are different priesthoods and different ministries
But in all of those we need to be looking not for the thing we want the thing we desire the thing we think will make us happy
But what we feel compelled and driven by the spirit of God to do
you.
Those are my last thoughts.
Amen.
Well, that is our show for tonight.
Thank you very much everyone for listening.
If you didn't get through to us live, we'd still love to hear from you.
You can email us at Lord of Spirit at ancientfeath.com.
You can message us at our Facebook page or you can leave us a voice mail at speakpipe.com
slash Lord of Spirits.
And join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m.
Eastern 4pm Pacific except the next one which will be premed.
And if you are on Facebook, you can like our page, you can join our discussion group,
leave reviews and ratings in all the appropriate places, but most importantly, share this
show with a friend who will be edified by it.
Heck, leave some inappropriate places.
And finally, be sure to go to www.hfafet.com, stroke support, and help make sure we and lots
of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
But if you listen to those other podcas, don't tell me, because I get a little bit gang
as calm.
Thank you very much.
Good night, God bless you, and hey, everybody remember, subscribe to The Wolf and the Cross.
It's my awesome documentary that's gonna release anytime now.
Free commercial.
around about the throne and the beasts and the elders.
And the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000
and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice,
worthy is the land that was slain to receive power
and riches and wisdom and strength and honor
and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter five, verses 11 through 12.
I see the bridal